David S. Kong: Can you send me something?
Eric Rosenbaum: just…
David S. Kong: Wait, Schwartz, did you send me something?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I didn't, I didn't actually send you a link, I just sent you the track name. It's, Fear of the Unknown and the Blazing Sun.
David S. Kong: Oh, oh, thank you, oh, I got it, I got it, I got it. I got it, I got it, I got it, thank you.
Eric Rosenbaum: And I gave, you know, Claude access to the source material.
Eric Rosenbaum: And it generated a report, including, like, a roster of 15 distinct named dragonids.
Eric Rosenbaum: from the ZCC harvest, and a whole, like… in-depth.
Eric Rosenbaum: Explanation of what they are in that world, so…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Alright, y'all, I'm super psyched for this.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): This is the music I was listening to over and over and over, while prepping for today, and I think it's just the right amount of deeply strange,
David S. Kong: We're the one.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh, we're not getting it.
David S. Kong: I know.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, crank it up, huh? I'll be right back.
David S. Kong: Yep. And we loved… Hold on.
David S. Kong: Hold on, hold on… Okay.
David S. Kong: There it is.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Of all the wires… It was the wires.
David S. Kong: Are you hearing anything?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: That were the wires for empathy?
Mike Sackton: the wires.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: There we are.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: We're just getting the speech, not the music sounds, I think.
Mike Sackton: The news is coming.
Eric Rosenbaum: There it is.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: The others… All the wires… It was the wires.
Eric Rosenbaum: I sense the tone shifting.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Feeding.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: We love beyond all the others.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Sound of that…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Streaming.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: It's see the smell.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: The paper tree.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And dogs travel back and forth.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: The blazing sun. Wow.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I can see you, I can hear the song.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So tell your secrets to parents.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Dear lost father, and to his Father, and to his Father.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: This conversation itself just… The substitute.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: It's rather…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Because this is the season finale, the previously on section is gonna be a little longer.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But here's the…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: story so far.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Oh, I don't wait.
Eric Rosenbaum: in here.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh. Yes.
Mike Sackton: Sounds fair.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: The five of you are, in this moment, standing in…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Something that's darker than blackness, having just passed through the door into the prison.
David S. Kong: An image?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, just, blackness.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Tim.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): In fact, if you've got any colors that are, like, blacker than black, like the absence of the possibility of color, that would be perfect.
Eric Rosenbaum: And we should make sure to record.
Tim Sackton: It's recording already.
Eric Rosenbaum: Hold on. Okay, good. Okay.
Tim Sackton: I don't know if I can do just pure black.
Tim Sackton: I mean, I can just get a pure black image.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So you've stepped through…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): into the prison, with the door closing behind, dodging out of the way, cleverly, quickly, from the grasping hands of Ministheus, now fully transformed into a mushroom man.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Here's how you got here.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Last spring, the embittered adventurer Hulda received a 400-year-old deed of inheritance. Perfect. Written in oddly contemporary language.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): To a manor house at the wild northern edges of the Duchy of Tellum.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: There was one condition.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Go through the door in the cellar of the house, and convince the Fae lord on the other side to break a promise once made.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Lord Endlessly Ending had been tricked into his compact by the wizard Thelestria, head of the Drancorian order Erythramos Limperum in the waning days of the Empire.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Each time a clock she gave him struck zero.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Lord Ending would send a mortal guest at his party through the doors of her house.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That compact has held to the present, 700 years later, though for the Feylord, it was merely struck earlier, in the same endless celebration he still hosts.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Hulda hires the party, who travel to the Feylord's Revel, where Tarek steals a yet-to-be-disclosed possession of that lord, and the party meets guests from across centuries, including a curious Rakshasa, Tigerman.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The Fae is unable to break his promise.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But asks them to bring him the key to the prison door at the center of the house.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Presumably because if he breaks it and the prisoner goes free, his promise becomes irrelevant.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Joined by Manistheus, a member of the Lestria's party who she left behind when she made the bargain, the group enters the house of 27 rooms.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Surrounding a central prison chamber, the Order built the house as a magical and mechanical device to untether the central prison room from the world around it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And to keep the physical and the temporal location of that central room constantly changing. If it stopped moving somehow, the prisoner would quickly escape.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Each movement through a doorway between rooms in the house shifts the physical or temporal coordinates of the prison.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And in that way, the randomness of mortal choices kept the prisoner from knowing where or when they were or what to expect was coming.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the steady supply of mortals, by the Lord endlessly ending, has kept it in constant motion to this day.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The party makes their way through the house, fighting off fungal-transformed attackers, one of whom infects meniscus badly.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And realizes that Hulda's servant who hired them.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The servants they saw at the house, too, were these same mushroom men.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): They meet Calypsies, an ancient dwarven wizard, putting the final touches on a fungal golem body.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Into which she intends to transfer her consciousness and restart the erythromos limperum.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): They collect a clock and bring it with them, which always gives the.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Ever-shifting year inside of the central room.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And finally, and Eric, this is what you missed last session.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You come to the library and talk with a clockwork magical research assistant, who, unnamed, they give the name Array to.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Array helps them to understand… sorry, I should have written it in the second person. Array helps you to understand that the house is powered by the energy of trapped souls prevented from moving on to their afterlife, like water trapped behind a dam.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): They read from the order's Erythrama Slim Parum's Allegories for the Initiated.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Odd stories about…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Hedgehogs made to kill.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And monkey trap prisons?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Where it's just large enough for the monkey to put its hand in, but when it closes its fist around what's inside and tries to take it out, it can't?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): mindless things that imitate minds, and then Aray writes a personal allegory for each of them. And with apologies, Tarek, that was the one thing I didn't have time to prep for you this week.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: At the prison door.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You see 3 doors simultaneously over each other.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And they each lead to rooms in which you can see the three different voices you've heard
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): through the walls in your wanderings, and read from in the transcribed notebooks. A child, A young adult.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And a deeply crazed middle-aged man who appears vastly older.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): As you open the door to the room with the child, Monistheus, now fully transformed into a mushroom man, attacks, but dodging him, you step through and close the door behind you, and stand now in an utter darkness, in something darker than darkness, in the absence even of the possibility of color, or form, or light.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): as the clock.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): that, Tarek, I think, is still carrying strikes zero.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): In the darkness, I would love to open with, A brief character description.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Despite the absence of anything visible.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And… What is the hope and the fear that you're experiencing in this moment?
Eric Rosenbaum: Tarek must have kind of blacked out, and is still recovering?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So he's experiencing…
Eric Rosenbaum: Confusion, discombobulation.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The last room, too, was a… was a library, so…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Perhaps you found a book that was just absorbing and ignored what was going on?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But he's also… A little puzzled by the sensation of the clock striking zero, because clearly it makes…
Eric Rosenbaum: Zero chimes allowed, so how do you even know that that has occurred?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But he knows it nonetheless.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I suppose I should tell… everyone.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But in his confusion, he, only mumble something.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: It struck… it struck zero?
Mike Sackton: Edrek is…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I mean, you can't see them, it's pitch black.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But I think there's still…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: A sense of him in the space, large and…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Trying to be brave and comforting?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Whether anybody senses that.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: is not… I don't know, it's up to you guys.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: his… his… Fear…
Mike Sackton: Which he probably wouldn't admit to. Well, he has two fears, one of which he probably would admit to, and one of which he probably wouldn't.
Mike Sackton: That he would admit to is just he's afraid he's gotten himself into something that's gonna… Peril his soul.
Mike Sackton: In the literal, not in the modern Christian sense of the word or anything like that, but in the literal sense of, is this going to eat my soul?
Mike Sackton: has…
Mike Sackton: Pierre that maybe he wouldn't admit to is… does he… does he even know who the good guys and the bad guys are?
Mike Sackton: And… is he doing the right thing by making assumptions about.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Which ones are which?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Although he's pretty confident from what we learned last session about who they could get.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: His hope is that…
Mike Sackton: we can…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: breathe, break the prison and breed this creature and end the necromantic…
Mike Sackton: soul-eating…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: mechanism that…
Mike Sackton: He believes is now the source of all these problems.
David S. Kong: Yo!
David S. Kong: Oh, sorry, go ahead.
Tim Sackton: No, you know.
David S. Kong: Cato has been such a rollercoaster this whole… this whole journey.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And it's really deeply affected him.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: This whole…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I mean, this is so far out of the standard realm of, like, the kind of, you know, tricks and conquests that he's used to doing with Tarek, and just sort of the, you know…
David S. Kong: performing and getting, you know, some… or whatever, whatever kind of mercenary stuff that they've been doing, and the tricks and games. And there's something about this return to total blackness and the void that is hitting Cato.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Deep right now.
David S. Kong: And there's something ancestral and ancient and timeless about this moment that, for him.
David S. Kong: There's a certain way in which the material life and all the shit in Tolin and whatever, it just has all evaporated, and he has gone someplace, like, pretty…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Like…
David S. Kong: sacred, and…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Nothing, and void, and he doesn't even know who he is anymore, or what.
David S. Kong: He's lost all sense of, kind of, identity in this moment, and doesn't know.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Time, direction, anything else.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Charlie?
Tim Sackton: is a tiny, maybe 6 inch long brown anole.
Tim Sackton: Having just wild shape to escape.
Tim Sackton: The tentacle of… Manestheus.
Tim Sackton: Moments ago.
Tim Sackton: You cannot hear or see him, but at the moment he is… likely trying to run up Edric's…
Tim Sackton: Leg, so it's to not be stepped on.
Tim Sackton: And…
Tim Sackton: Possibly wishing that he were a tiger instead of a lizard at this moment, as he looks into the darkness, which is presumably unpenetrable even with darkvision.
Tim Sackton: And wonders… Where the way home is.
Tim Sackton: And if he will be able to find that.
Kate Sackton: Aveen had been feeling pretty good about
Kate Sackton: What they learned in the library, and they had a plan, and maybe understood what they were going to be able to do to help people.
Kate Sackton: And then… Inside this prison… There's no light.
Kate Sackton: And… everything… that she… you know, draws…
Kate Sackton: inspiration and reassurance from is finding the light, and…
Kate Sackton: You know, bringing the light, and so… She's just taking a pause.
Kate Sackton: see… how… Continuing to… Do good and help.
Kate Sackton: Could possibly look.
Kate Sackton: When there's not light.
Kate Sackton: Maybe it'll be temporary.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): tied to one of your backs is RA, the sort of a bust of a,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Human, made from… Porcelain and wire… And paint and steel.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But if RA has opinions on what's going on.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): They don't share them at this moment.
Eric Rosenbaum: How do you spell that name?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): A-r-r-a-e.
David S. Kong: AKA Kato's best friend.
Eric Rosenbaum: A chatbot? Your best friend's a chatbot? That's weird.
David S. Kong: You said that part a little too loud.
Eric Rosenbaum: I don't know.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): This space that you're in is lightless, There's no sound?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Not that it's muffled, but there's just nothing making sound.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And silent.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): What? What would y'all like to do?
David S. Kong: Schwartz, is the feeling like… We're floating?
David S. Kong: Or are we standing on anything? Or is it… you know what I mean? Like, what's the sensation in the body?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Gravity and physical space, you're standing on something.
Mike Sackton: EJ's gonna… Cast light.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Nothing happens.
Mike Sackton: like… Describe nothing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, that's such…
Mike Sackton: The spell doesn't work, or the light is invisible, but the spell works.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You're still able to make a connection to the Light Queen… Night Queen, so the…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The spell spells, it's not like it's counterspelled, or unable to be cast, it's just when casting, no light is produced.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Presumably that… the conclusion you draw is that there's some effect… some magical effect suppressing, yeah.
Mike Sackton: So it's like… it's like what would happen if you cast the light spell, then put a… put a… put a rock… put a…
Mike Sackton: Because, like, it doesn't shine through couple, so it presumably.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yes, right, right. The spell is cast, there's just nothing…
Mike Sackton: There's just something blocking the light, so you can't actually see it. Like, it's surrounded by tinfoil or something.
Eric Rosenbaum: Tarek puts the clock… Up to his ear.
Eric Rosenbaum: What?
Eric Rosenbaum: Or I'm just sort of investigating the clock with my fingers, too, like… Maybe shake it a little.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Can you roll me an investigation check?
Eric Rosenbaum: Okay.
Eric Rosenbaum: 13.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): For 13, you remember that the clock striking zero was the same thing that happened at Lord Endless's party, that was the cue to send another mortal into the house.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Right.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): With a 13, you can also tell that the,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You know, the numbers that change on the clock are printed onto these little wheels, or little dials, and they are just slightly embossed in the printing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So with a couple of minutes of study, you could probably figure out
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): What the numbers and what the year was right now.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And if you want to work on that, we'll follow up on that in a minute.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yes, I used my…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Sensitive lock-picking fingertips to read.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Perfect. So you succeed, it'll just take a minute to figure it out.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: There's no…
Kate Sackton: Sound we're perceiving, or light we're perceiving… from…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: space we're in. We feel grappy.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: soybean…
Kate Sackton: Sort of reaches out and also says, Can you all hear me?
Mike Sackton: I assume we can hear a bean.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yes, you all can hear her.
Mike Sackton: Yes!
Kate Sackton: Oh, that's something.
Mike Sackton: I mean…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Hey.
Mike Sackton: can we, like, just reach out? Can I… we're not, like… it's just darkness, right? We're not, like… we can feel each other.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, you can feel each other. When you reach back to touch the door that you came through, it does not exist on this side of the wall. It's a smooth wall behind you.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): When you reach in the other direction, you realize you're standing on a very small patch of smooth floor that quickly gives way
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): To something that you recognize by touch, as woody or bony, or almost like coral that's been left behind after the animal in it has died?
Mike Sackton: Like, a wall, or on the ground?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: On the ground.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Ropes and roots and chutes, shoots of it.
Tim Sackton: No.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: to the tunnel we came through to get here.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It's not a tunnel, but it's the same stuff.
Tim Sackton: I'm gonna run up the wall behind us, is there a ceiling?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): There is. You, oh, actually, as you get maybe 10 feet out.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The stone wall starts to give way to these roots and branches and blobby coral structures.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And things that you can't tell what they are, but give you the impression that they are, like, the… almost, like, sculptural, like an… an imitation of face, or hands, or something like that. It's difficult to tell in the dark.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But it starts to angle out, so you can keep proceeding up, but you're… you're moving more at, like, a 30 or 40 degree angle towards the center of the room than straight up towards the ceiling.
Tim Sackton: So, like, the… the wa… the…
Kate Sackton: The wall has, like, an eave.
Tim Sackton: As an Eve? Okay.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, and Eve, that's not the substance of the wall itself, but the substance of that stuff.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): root stuff.
Tim Sackton: I guess we keep going forward. What other choice do we have?
Tim Sackton: You hear this little lizard voice say above you.
Tim Sackton: Kong, did you see my message?
David S. Kong: That's a good idea.
Mike Sackton: Yeah, I mean…
Eric Rosenbaum: Tarek says, hold on there, I've almost got it.
David S. Kong: Schwartz, I'll detect, The tech thoughts.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Boom.
David S. Kong: I can sense the presence of thoughts within 30 feet of myself that belong to creatures that know languages or are telepathic. I can't read the thoughts, but I know that a thinking creature is present. Nice.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): A thinking creature is present that can use language and is telepathic. The year is 1351. That's a little bit more than 400 years ago.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh, oh dear.
David S. Kong: How do I know that?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I've just done that.
Eric Rosenbaum: I… I let everybody know.
Eric Rosenbaum: That's, what-what?
Mike Sackton: the… the year?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: What do you mean? What is…
Eric Rosenbaum: What's weird.
Eric Rosenbaum: They're on the clock.
Eric Rosenbaum: When that's true.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: zero, which is now, I suppose. Or was now.
Eric Rosenbaum: Does that coincide with the contractual agreement?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It's… close… Yeah.
Eric Rosenbaum: form after?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): 1352 was the deed's origination date.
Eric Rosenbaum: I said to just… what year before.
Eric Rosenbaum: Of strange.
Tim Sackton: Charles said again, I really think we just go talk to this creature, whatever it is.
Eric Rosenbaum: Where is it?
Mike Sackton: Yeah?
Tim Sackton: It's within 30 feet of us.
Tim Sackton: Just… Tiny lizard voice. Hello?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm gonna answer that in just a sec, but Kong… I'll say in this case, your detect thoughts…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): There's an obfuscation, or there's something strange about it, because on the one hand, there is very clearly a creature.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): A creature that is thinking, and is…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You're able to use language and telepathic mind.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But on the other hand, It's almost like you're hearing, like, a distant chorus of voices.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Like, a murmuration of…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You know how if you walk, you know, you're on, like, the…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Second or third floor balcony above a room where there's a hundred people talking with each other, and it's just, it's that… it's that feeling, but with thoughts.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So there are two different categories of things going on with those.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Sorry, Tim, can you say that again?
Tim Sackton: I just said, hello?
Tim Sackton: In common.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I am looking at your dreaming, says a voice inside of all of your heads at once.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It is very lovely.
David S. Kong: Who are you?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I am being a child now.
David S. Kong: Who are your parents?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I'm not knowing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): There, being on the far side of the well.
Tim Sackton: Where is the well?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: The well is being cured just… Where I am.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But not inside the walls.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I am not seeing it from inside.
Eric Rosenbaum: Are you trapped here?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yes.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Why?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: You know why?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I'm grown?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And the first dreamer I have ever seen is coming to me.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And I'm seeing his dream.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And it's beautiful, and I'm keeping it.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And the second dreamer is coming, and I see that dream, too.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And I am keeping that one, and not letting it go. And the dreamers are coming by the dozens.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: These dreamers are carrying the cold metal.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the sticks that make heat, and they scare me, and they praise me, and they say they have more dreams to give me. They say, I am helpful. They are saying, I can keep the dreams so that no one can find them.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That when I keep the dreams, I am hiding them.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): They're saying that some dreams are bad dreams, and that I am good at hiding them.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But every dream is beautiful to me, and I am keeping them.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): They're saying that if I am promising to keep every dream they bring me, they are building me a house to play in. And if I live inside the house, they are bringing more dreams. And I am inside the house, and the walls are cold.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I cannot sleep, and I cannot leave, but they're bringing me more dreams.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh, yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Watching the dreams.
Eric Rosenbaum: You're at the Beaver Dam.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): to the dreams listening to me outside the walls, and I am asking them to let me go home, and they are telling me it is too important that I eat the dreams they bring to me.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: They're telling me the door to my house does not open big enough for me to go.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): and my teacher.
Eric Rosenbaum: Sure.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: is not coming.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And the only thing with me is the dreams. And the dreams are wanting to leave, but I am not letting them.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Because I am being alone without them, and nothing is moving.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And everything is changing.
Mike Sackton: Where's home?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Home is being at the bottom of the bottomless well.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The house they're making for me is not my home.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: After you appreciate the dreams that you've had per company.
Kate Sackton: Would you let them go if you went to your home at the bottom of the bottom as well?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I do not…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Let the dreams go.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Why am I letting the dreams go?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Being with you is not the dream's home.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Like, this house they built for you is not your home?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It pauses in a long silence.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That suggests both…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It knew you were going to say that, and it didn't want to face that.
Eric Rosenbaum: Hmm.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I cannot see what your dreams are doing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I like this always.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): When dreams are coming to me.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: There is a deciding.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I am not knowing what is happening.
Eric Rosenbaum: Hmm…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: When dreams are coming to me, There is a curiosity.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I am not knowing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): What the questions are being.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Tell us about one of the dreams.
Eric Rosenbaum: You've already got?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I am telling you a story if you are telling me a story, too.
Eric Rosenbaum: Hmm, that's… That seems only fair.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): My teacher is sitting with me next to the well.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And he's teaching me How to speak in stories that dreamers can understand.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: We're sitting next to the well, and my teacher explains.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): About how words make before and after.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: How words make stories about befores and afters.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And he is leaving, and his party is starting.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And he is coming back when it has ended. And I'm next to my well for a very long time. I'm liking how still the world is.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And everything is moving, and nothing is changing, the wind.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): is moving the grass, and the bright stars are just coming out, and I am watching, and watching, and the smell of my home is nearby in the well.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I am not going home, because I am very quiet, and very still, and very happy.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The first dreamer is coming to me.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I used the words that my teacher taught me.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The dreamer… is, like, you.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: It walks with two legs.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: It is not knowing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The shape of its own possibility.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): becomes…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Down the road?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And it's walking up and up to where I am sitting.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And it is speaking in words to me, and I am speaking back.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: That dream… Is a curious dream.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: That dream is a singing dream.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: She's still here.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: She sings sometimes.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Less and less.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: That dream… Sang to me the story of its travels, And sang me… Story of light?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I told it a story from my home.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Then it was just a shining dream and nothing else, and it stayed with me ever since.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: What is the story of a dream that you know?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: What is the story of your dream?
Eric Rosenbaum: Once… When I was younger than I am now.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I was exploring.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: A place I thought I knew well, near where I grew up.
Eric Rosenbaum: And I fell through the floor.
Eric Rosenbaum: I was hurt.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But in the beam of light from above.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I saw some very old things.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: around me.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And they were from… Another people.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And these things, I thought.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Maybe they could help me.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And no one would mind if I just… took.
Eric Rosenbaum: One or two.
Eric Rosenbaum: And I found my way out.
Eric Rosenbaum: And after that.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I knew, or I thought I knew, the shape of my own possibilities.
Eric Rosenbaum: Because those things…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: That I had borrowed, or taken.
Eric Rosenbaum: Other people were very interested in them.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And I could get the things that I needed and wanted as a result.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I am watching your dream.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And it falls silent, and you get the impression that… it's reflecting
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): To itself, and, withdrawing from conversation for at least a bit.
David S. Kong: Tim… is it talking to us, like, in a voice that we can hear? Like, can we place… is it, like, somebody speaking in front of us? Or, like, can we, like, do we locationally know where they are?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It is speaking psychically, but you do have a sense that it is a thing that it…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Nonetheless, that there is a location
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Sort of toward the back, towards the top of the room.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): This room, like all the others, is a 30-foot cube.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And, Charles' investigation suggests that, like, it's almost like a root-bound plant that has grown to fill the entire space of its pot, except maybe a relatively small open area where you are now. But that's somewhere towards the back, towards the top, is the center of the thing itself.
David S. Kong: But the entity is there.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yes.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So this thing… Is the monkey's paw forming the beaver dam?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: If you know what I'm saying.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Never hear the dark.
Eric Rosenbaum: What's that?
Kate Sackton: Yes, we hear you, jerk.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: It's the monkey's paw, because what it's holding prevents it from escaping.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Which are all just mortal souls.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But if it releases them… Well, then what happens?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Good.
Eric Rosenbaum: The dam breaks.
Eric Rosenbaum: And this…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Oh, prison?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Powered by the pressure.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Have the soul's wish to return… Or depart. Or die.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: We'll see to function.
Eric Rosenbaum: And it releases… What?
Kate Sackton: read this.
Kate Sackton: Entity who we're calling the prisoner.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Has…
Kate Sackton: Some attributes that are plant-like.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And is a collector of souls, but can live in his home at the bottom of the bottomless well.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Happily experiencing…
Kate Sackton: Familiar smells and stars.
Kate Sackton: Not someone, too.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Souls.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So it has a natural place in existence. People can get involved.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Being a soul track.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So we could send it back there.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: If we can persuade it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): We don't agree to.
Tim Sackton: I'm gonna crawl around, are there any other exits from this room?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): yes. In the corner off…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): sort of to your right, as you're still sort of standing by the entrance. There is…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You know, you go a foot or two in, and then realizing where you are back, back out again.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): A hollow, root-like structure That seems to you almost identical to the one which you crawled from the,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): From Taelgar to the Feywild through.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): a room that's…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): At least by its, sort of, dimensions and size and shape, suggests that it's grown out of the prison.
Kate Sackton: The rate that prisoners have been coming…
Kate Sackton: Hasn't quite enough to maintain 100%.
Kate Sackton: The rate that mortals have been coming has been quite enough to maintain 100% prison structural integrity.
Kate Sackton: So there's a root.
Kate Sackton: And the mushroom men got out, too.
Kate Sackton: Our world, and… We're able to be servants, and they got…
Kate Sackton: out into the Feywild, and we're able to be… Dangerous.
Tim Sackton: Oh, it's gonna turn back into a…
Tim Sackton: Lizardfolk. It's a little bit easier to talk.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Kiddo asks…
David S. Kong: What do you want?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): There's a tremble in the voice of the thing as it responds, and says, almost like fear, it says.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm not… knowing, and I'm not… Knowing why I'm not knowing.
Eric Rosenbaum: beam.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm missing… my teacher, I am missing my home.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm loving… The dreams that I've collected.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I'm not letting them go.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm not knowing, and I am not knowing why I'm not knowing.
Mike Sackton: Can you tell us a story about your teacher?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I will tell you a story about your future.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: No, teacher.
Mike Sackton: I said teacher. Yeah, teacher, not…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Teacher. Teacher, not future.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Yeah. Sure.
Mike Sackton: Can you tell us a story about your teacher?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: When my teacher is finding me, I am being very small.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the world is being very, very big.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): When my teacher is finding me.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I'm not knowing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): What this place is…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I am not knowing words.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): My teacher is very patient.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: My teacher… It is very nice, and explains things to me.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And my teacher is having to leave, and I am not wanting my teacher to leave.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But my teacher is having to leave. My teacher is explaining.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: He is saying, he is part of a story.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And everything here is part of a story. And there are words for before and after.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And he is having to do his part of the story.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And he is coming to me after.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And he is believing that.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But I am knowing it is not true, and I am not seeing him again.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I am sad, because I am loving him.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Now you'll tell me a story about your teacher.
Mike Sackton: My teacher is, power beyond understanding.
Mike Sackton: that… guides… That… watches over us.
Mike Sackton: As we transition, From life to death, from death to death to life, and makes the night safe.
Mike Sackton: And… She teaches me to… Have faith every day.
Mike Sackton: That the night will be safe.
Mike Sackton: No matter what.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: else happens.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I am seeing this.
Mike Sackton: Your teacher seems…
Mike Sackton: Where did your teacher go?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): My teacher is going back to his house, where his party is beginning.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): is saying.
Eric Rosenbaum: the Lord.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Right.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): pointing.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Charo keeps glancing over at the… Bole in the floor.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And looks to everybody and says, Why don't we just leave?
Eric Rosenbaum: And go where?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: There's a tunnel through the roots over there.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Very much like the tunnel we came into this.
Tim Sackton: Cursed realm from.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Oh, you think we could just… Gah who?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I do not know where it leads, but…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: That isn't a guess.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Okay.
David S. Kong: We're having this conversation telepathically or out loud?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Out loud, the voice in your head seems telepathic, but you're responding out loud.
David S. Kong: What would you have us do?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Dreamers are being difficult, always, to explain to.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And you being here, and your dreams are confusing to me, and I cannot see what they are doing.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I am bringing you here.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm not knowing what is happening next.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Do you want us to stay or go?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Or bring you.
David S. Kong: Or something else.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm not…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I am not a thing that wants.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It makes the dreams I've collected very confusing, because I do want them.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm not a choosing thing, like the dreamers are choosing things.
Eric Rosenbaum: The dreamers like… To leave you?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): A pebble in your pocket is wanting to fall to the ground as soon as it can.
Eric Rosenbaum: Shit.
Tim Sackton: I'm gonna look over at Katerman.
Tim Sackton: And sort of say, under my breath, why do we care what it wants?
David S. Kong: How do we go home?
Mike Sackton: No, we can't weep this.
Tim Sackton: Why not?
Mike Sackton: It's eating souls and doesn't know any better.
Eric Rosenbaum: Maybe we can convince it to let them all go, but then what would happen?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Dude.
Mike Sackton: They go to the land of the dead and where they belong.
Mike Sackton: Hopefully.
Eric Rosenbaum: Well, doesn't that seem like it would be beneficial?
Mike Sackton: Yes!
Mike Sackton: Glad we can't leave.
Kate Sackton: When dreamers don't have bodies anymore… sorry, Kato, were you about to say something?
Kate Sackton: when… Dreamers?
Kate Sackton: Dreams will stay with you.
Kate Sackton: But another form can leave.
Kate Sackton: Those have gone from this place.
Kate Sackton: They've gone and… many directions.
Kate Sackton: Have you helped guide where they leave when they leave through the exit?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Or…
Kate Sackton: Is that not something…
Kate Sackton: As you said, you're not… you do not choose. Do you not choose where the dreamers go, or the…
Kate Sackton: We call them mushroom people.
Kate Sackton: Where they go, when they leave.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Sometimes when the dreamers come into this room.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): My children, who are not knowing any better.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Find a home inside of them.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And grow until there's no more Dreamer and only my children?
Kate Sackton: So when your children have left here.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: in…
Kate Sackton: What used to be a dreamer, but is not anymore. It is all your children.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Is it chance where they go?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The ones who built my playhouse.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The ones who built my playhouse kept me… from seeing where I am.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And when I am.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Wow.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Not that that's real.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): They made it… So that they are the ones who are controlling where I am, and when I am.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And therefore, they are the ones who control where and when my children go, When they leave.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Out through the root that I grew before everything began moving.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So when I send my children out.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And two, when I send out the ones
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Who did not become my children.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I am sending them… Like seeds scattered on the wind, not knowing where they will land.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I have no way of knowing where and when I am.
Kate Sackton: So if we know where and when we are, And we leave.
Kate Sackton: That is where we will be.
Kate Sackton: Through the route.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Where and when it is inside the room is where and when it is on the far side of the root. That is the nature of the thing.
Kate Sackton: What year did you say it was, Tarek?
Eric Rosenbaum: 1551, I think?
Mike Sackton: I don't wanna go there.
Eric Rosenbaum: That's not our time.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): 1851?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That is a funny time.
Eric Rosenbaum: What's funny about it?
Eric Rosenbaum: Panihaha.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That is the time that Old Hulda went to.
David S. Kong: Who? Old Hoga?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Old hull… holder.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Yeah.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Wait.
Mike Sackton: Did he set himself up in some sort of time loop?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): the thing… Laughs to itself.
Mike Sackton: I'm not sure if Egypt… well, no Egypt would have said that, well, just kill it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Dreamers are being difficult, always.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm seeing… The shape of your dream's possibility?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And it is being your future.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): All of you are being 20 years older?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Tarek, you are being a father to your children.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And Ivine, you are helping your parents' dream drift home? And Charo, you are caring for a whole village. And Kato Min, you are not being adrift, you are going home. And Edric, you are not being in the world at all. You are at the gate, where your godmother stands.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): In this possibility, Old Hulda is not getting deed for my bones.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Old Hulda is adventuring still. Old Hulda is being angry all the time, and hurt, and sad, and is finding door in my bones, and crawling through tunnel, and is walking road, and is opening door, and is talking to me, right now, inside this house. I am telling him.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You are old and angry and ending.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I am telling him.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Crawl through the hole in my floor, and it is being 400 years ago without you being born.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You are writing letters on paper, and giving it to a man who is giving it back to a younger you.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You are writing a promise. To break the agreement of my teacher.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And you are keeping house and reward, and best of all, younger you is not becoming you.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And he is doing it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Old Man Hulda is crawling through hole and dying.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But young man Holta is getting my deed, and my children are helping find you, and you are being here, and your dreams are confusing me, and I cannot see what they are doing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And this is the fourth time now.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That one of the seeds I've cast out into the world has sent someone back to me.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I am hoping that this is the last time, and I am not knowing.
Eric Rosenbaum: Wow.
Eric Rosenbaum: That explains, and yet also fails to explain, everything.
Eric Rosenbaum: I love it.
David S. Kong: What the fuck is going on?
Eric Rosenbaum: What are my kids' names?
Eric Rosenbaum: No, no, wait. I don't want to know, because they may never come to be.
Eric Rosenbaum: The fourth time?
Eric Rosenbaum: What were the others?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Peace.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It's silent. It's silent.
Eric Rosenbaum: Anteloops are hard to reason about.
Eric Rosenbaum: Time limbs are hard to reason about.
Kate Sackton: Our dreams are confusing, alright.
David S. Kong: This is the fourth time.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Not that is with all of you specifically, but the fourth time
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): that he has sent someone out into the world who has returned others to Him.
David S. Kong: So before…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It's ambiguous whether all four of those were Holder or whether those four were different.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): People are different versions, or…
David S. Kong: Yeah, so I mean, like.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: The fourth experiment, or the fourth…
David S. Kong: iteration of the…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The fourth run, yeah. The fourth one that's good at a result, yeah.
David S. Kong: Olga's number 4, and there were 3 others.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: What are we- what the fuck are we supposed to do? So…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: You want this to be the last time, we want this to be the last time, what do we do? E-Jake literally just says that out loud.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I am not knowing how to let go…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Of the dreams that I've collected.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I found…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Upon learning…
Eric Rosenbaum: How to make it.
Eric Rosenbaum: Without anyone else knowing.
Eric Rosenbaum: Things could end up in my pockets.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: That it all went much better after that.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: If they came out again.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I take things and I give them back away.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: In fact… I've got this thing, if you happen to know what it is.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I don't.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm gonna challenge back, actually.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I need you to describe what this thing is.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And especially what its significance is.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh, no.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: You'd think.
Eric Rosenbaum: Well, I'll just use the first thing that came to mind.
Eric Rosenbaum: It's a cup, a small one.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I've been carrying it around in this… A velvet bag.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I think I found it in the bag.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Anyway, through the bag, you can kind of feel that it's… it's…
Eric Rosenbaum: Heavily ornamented.
Eric Rosenbaum: What would you drink from such a cup? That I don't know.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Who's drinking from this cup?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And what is on this cup?
Eric Rosenbaum: It came from your teacher's house.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I would take it out and look, but…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I'm out here. I cannot see.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I didn't see it. You feel something in it… soften.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: My teacher… He's telling me… That stories…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Are what make before and after?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: My teacher is telling me… that stories…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): bind him.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Require him.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oblige him.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I'll say mechanically, In order to convince him to let go of the souls,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Each of you has a persuasion check that you can make.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): If you tell him a compelling story,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That in an extremely open-ended way.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): in form and format and content and purpose, I mean, in as open-ended a way as you can imagine, among all the stories that you've encountered in the Feywild so far.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): a story…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: who's really.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The result is that he might let go of souls, or some of them, or all of them.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Yes.
Eric Rosenbaum: Sorry about ourselves, or about someone else, or…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Or about him, or about the future, or about the past, or about…
Eric Rosenbaum: A name?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): for the present moment that you're in right now that reshapes it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): the way Felestria did with Endless, or an allegory, like the allegories written for you, or…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: a history.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, some of what's been told.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Or…
Eric Rosenbaum: Hmm…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm intending it extraordinarily broadly.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I would love you to…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Sort of give me the rationale of what you're hoping the story would accomplish, and then to…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Tell it.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So I think, essentially, rather than.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): A combat to resolve this, we're doing it as a storytelling contest.
Tim Sackton: Charo, who has never told a persuasive or convincing story in his entire life.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Sits down and thinks.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Arik reflects on the nature of… Taking…
Eric Rosenbaum: And giving things back.
Eric Rosenbaum: And notices that he still has this… Lord's Cup.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Alrighty.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Egypt.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Agent.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: It's not necessarily an effective story.
Mike Sackton: But I think Egypt's gonna do this anyway.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: is what… what… so I wanna… so, first of all, the general… idea.
Mike Sackton: of what Energy would do.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: would be to… Show… the…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So the story is basically about how these come to discover… I don't…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I'm couching this because I need to ask you a question, a mechanic question, but,
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Egypt wants to basically, convince him that he's…
Mike Sackton: This is… that he's not being kind and nice in the dream, and then when he's taking the dreamers, he's violating the order of the gods, and that this is a horrible thing he's doing, and that you should stop because it's so bad.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Rev.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Mmm.
Mike Sackton: And… and I wanna… I wanna enter a rage.
Mike Sackton: as his, like, zealot mode, and use Strength.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh, man.
Mike Sackton: instead of charisma.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yes. Fine.
Mike Sackton: On this story.
Eric Rosenbaum: I need to buy experience.
Mike Sackton: I need to find a dot, but I'll… I'll tell… I can just roll on the… I can just roll on the team. So… so Egypt's story is kind of like… so, like, he…
Mike Sackton: he, like, raised to the Night Queen, and… and, like, well, we're still in pitch darkness, right? So you can't actually see him, but you can hear his prayer.
Mike Sackton: And, again, you have this sense of, like, palpable…
Mike Sackton: This palpable sense of, like, religious fervor just in the room, like…
Mike Sackton: And this sense of, like, what is happening here is just raw, like, almost radiating from him, the sense of anger at the wrongness of what is happening.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And he tells, in sort of short, Short, static words, like… that…
Mike Sackton: the cycle, like, the mythology of souls, right? The basic story is, like, the core miracle of all humans.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But they are born, and then…
Mike Sackton: The gods grant them a miracle at birth?
Mike Sackton: passing their soul into Talgar.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And the gods grant every human a miracle at death.
Mike Sackton: Taking their soul back in to the divine outer realms, right?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And… and…
Mike Sackton: Egypt tells the story in, like, a very…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Religious.
Mike Sackton: flavor, right? Like, you know, the Night Queen mediates this, and… but real passion around, like, this is a miracle that every human deserves.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And you cannot… and you are taking this miracle away from them. You are… when you take their dreams, you are not allowing, you are preventing the gods from taking this soul back in and giving them the miracle of death that the Night Queen brings, and the miracle of peace.
Mike Sackton: And you think you are inspecting their dreams, and you do not know, you are not a human, you do not know what you're doing.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But it is wrong, and you need to stop, because you are hurting people.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And I've, like, learned this, like, from… so the beginning is all, like, the typical myth, right? And then he's like, and I've learned…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: What's happening, these people who… I forget her name, but
Audio shared by David S. Kong: the person who created the prison, like, changed it, like, she… she's trapped you, and convinced you, and made you do this thing where you are… you are hurting these people, and you are… you are not somebody who wants to hurt people, and you… you do not believe in hurting, so stop.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And let them go.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: To where they belong.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I love it. So, I have a threshold of the total number of souls that this thing has collected.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And for each of you, we're gonna take your role with modifiers and sum it up, and if the collective
Audio shared by David S. Kong: sum exceeds the threshold, it's gonna be a success as a group.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And if not.
Mike Sackton: I rolled a 4?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So that's… that's not very good.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: M… Having rolled a 4, but with strength instead of, would be a 7.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Do y'all not have, heroic inspiration?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Is that another thing?
Mike Sackton: It is a thing, I'm a human, I can't remember when did we last long rest.
Tim Sackton: You used it in the combat.
Mike Sackton: I think I used it in the combat.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I mean, I'm a bard, Got two bards.
Mike Sackton: Oh, everybody should have Barnick Inspirations. How many Barnik Inspirations do you guys have got?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Orgs.
Tim Sackton: Three or four total between the two of them?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I have two left.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I've got.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So many lives.
Mike Sackton: Wow, we should all take bardic inspiration, huh?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Yes, 100%. You should use it right now.
Mike Sackton: 5.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: to that.
Eric Rosenbaum: Nice.
Mike Sackton: Wow. Total.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): 12 total.
Mike Sackton: Unless I'm just looking at one thing,
Tim Sackton: No, no, no, you're raging, you have advantage.
Mike Sackton: I was gonna say, do I have advantage because I'm regions?
Tim Sackton: How you doing?
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh my gosh.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I do have an advantage, that's what I was looking at.
Mike Sackton: Wow, okay, that's 7. That's not that much better than a 4, but it's 15 instead of 12 total.
Eric Rosenbaum: That's more souls. There you go.
Mike Sackton: Oh, that was my last rage, too.
Kate Sackton: In the darkness.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Describe… sorry, Mike, describe, as you're coming out of that rage, of your last rage.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): What… what's your affect like? What's it like coming out of that rage? This one in particular?
Mike Sackton: AJ?
Mike Sackton: Normally, it's actually quite… normally Egypt comes out of rage, like, in the post-combat rush, and it's like…
Mike Sackton: a queer transition, and so he kind of flows through a little bit more easily. Here, he just, he, like, sits down, but you'll see it, but he just kind of almost collapses, like, he feels…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: like… Everything's gone now.
Mike Sackton: And it's up to the fate of the gods, and you can't influence it anymore.
Mike Sackton: He's just sitting on the ground now.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I love it.
David S. Kong: Plates of Schwartz. We're telling a story, and then… and then how does this relate to the rolling?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And then you're making a persuasion check with all whatever…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Whatever modifiers you can add to it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But you gotta tell… the story has to be effective, or it won't give you the role.
David S. Kong: Got it.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And it's gotta be about lettuce, like, something that would convince him to let go of souls.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Yep. Yes.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yes, and, I mean, I…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I think part of what I want to do is just make it really expansive. It's not merely, like.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): argument in favor of letting go of souls. Yes. But it could be any flavor or… I mean, it could be a fairy tale, it could be a…
David S. Kong: I got it, okay.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I wanna go next.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So… Kano Min… you can't see Kato Min, of course none of us can see fucking anything.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Again, this… being here… being here in this moment has been, like, honestly, kind of a religious experience for Tato Man.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And… He gets down on his knees.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: and kind of…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: You know, is in a… is facing in a general direction to where he hears the voice.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And… E.
David S. Kong: I guess he's thinking this in his mind, because he doesn't say this out loud, actually. This is more of a private conversation with the,
David S. Kong: With this voice, whomever… whomever this is.
David S. Kong: And Kato's basically, like.
David S. Kong: You love the dreamers and the souls.
David S. Kong: And I've also loved Dreamers and Souls.
David S. Kong: And I've loved… Being a trickster.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: The trickster.
David S. Kong: The one to show… Dreamers' Dreams.
David S. Kong: Enter it. The one to show souls.
David S. Kong: The way to use their souls.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And…
David S. Kong: So many dreams.
David S. Kong: Dreams.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But also stolen?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And kept for myself.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And…
David S. Kong: so many dreams.
David S. Kong: Have been lost.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: and not return.
David S. Kong: And those dreamers, they've… Lost the ability to dream, or they've… Maybe lost their own souls.
David S. Kong: But I didn't care.
David S. Kong: Because… I had their souls, and I had their dreams.
David S. Kong: And that made me very happy.
David S. Kong: It made me very, very happy.
David S. Kong: And I'm old.
David S. Kong: Relatively speaking. Not as… maybe not as old as you, I don't even know what time means here, but…
David S. Kong: I've also kept so many dreams and so many souls, and I thought, That… that made me happy.
David S. Kong: I thought that that gave me meaning.
David S. Kong: That every new soul that I kept, every new dream that I collected.
David S. Kong: Would somehow make me more full, and make me more… at peace.
David S. Kong: And maybe…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Help me to understand more of.
David S. Kong: Who I thought I was?
Audio shared by David S. Kong: But being here…
David S. Kong: Being in this nothingness, Being in this.
David S. Kong: total darkness.
David S. Kong: I actually don't remember anymore about the dreamers, or the dreams, or the souls, and the souls that…
David S. Kong: Or taken or lost.
David S. Kong: Here, there's nothing.
David S. Kong: There are no dreamers and no souls, for me.
David S. Kong: But something is different here for me.
David S. Kong: Something that's different here than I've felt out there.
David S. Kong: And… Even though there's no more Dreamers and no more souls.
David S. Kong: With all of that gone, now I can see who I am.
David S. Kong: And… I thought I knew what happiness was.
David S. Kong: But now, without any dreamers, without any souls, with just this nothingness, I'm not scared.
David S. Kong: I'm not… Empty, either.
David S. Kong: I think I'm… Happy for the first time.
David S. Kong: Ever.
David S. Kong: Here.
David S. Kong: in the nothingness.
David S. Kong: In the darkness. With no souls and no dreams.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Let me respond real quick before you roll it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): after Edric's story, Edric's story, the…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The sense was almost that the attention or focus of the prisoner was to the souls that it was holding, and Cato, after your story, the sense is almost that it's thinking of its home, it's thinking of the place and the thing that it was before and maybe after what it is here.
David S. Kong: Should I roll a D20?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Persuasion?
David S. Kong: Plus 7, baby, let's fucking go.
Eric Rosenbaum: What'd you get?
David S. Kong: I rolled a 1.
David S. Kong: Falls flat. Wait, wait, wait!
David S. Kong: Haha, I get, I get, I got special shit.
David S. Kong: I get to do all kinds of fucking shit,
David S. Kong: I have luck points that I can spend.
Mike Sackton: At what point?
David S. Kong: I spend a luck point to give myself advantage on a roll. So I spend one of my luck points.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): This feels like an appropriate time.
Eric Rosenbaum: Indeed.
David S. Kong: I will re-roll that. That one. I can't do any worse than that.
David S. Kong: Okay, this is much better, I got a 20.
Mike Sackton: Wait, really? You went from 1 to a 20?
David S. Kong: With… I rolled a 13.
Mike Sackton: Oh, I was gonna say, that would have been a good reversal of fortune.
David S. Kong: I mean, it's still pretty good, what, from 1 to a third.
Mike Sackton: Pretty good, yeah.
David S. Kong: No way, dude.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah. Bardic or other…
David S. Kong: I can do more, yeah, I can do more things. I can't do Bardic on myself, though, right?
Kate Sackton: You can have…
Tim Sackton: But a VIN can give you blood.
Mike Sackton: Spain can give.
David S. Kong: Oh!
Tim Sackton: I think we each have one bardic.
David S. Kong: Great.
Mike Sackton: Yeah.
David S. Kong: Cool, so I roll another D6.
Mike Sackton: Yep.
David S. Kong: Yeah.
David S. Kong: So let me roll another D6.
David S. Kong: 2.
David S. Kong: 22.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It was solid.
Eric Rosenbaum: Do we… is anything happening as a result?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Nothing is happening that's visible, but there's… there's a feeling, I mean, there's a feeling like a softening, a…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): a shift. I mean, if you're in a conversation with someone
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): you know, who is so skeptical, and you can watch, in the course of the conversation, their face sort of shift and open and begin to hear and receive. That is the feeling that you're having, though there's.
Eric Rosenbaum: Nothing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): to see that corresponds with it.
David S. Kong: I love it so much, it's like, are they bloodied? It's like, they're really, like, receptive and warm and loving. It's hilarious. They're bloodied.
Eric Rosenbaum: That's amazing.
David S. Kong: The best combat of all time. Great.
Eric Rosenbaum: Alright, so… You said to state the intention first?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, so, sort of, so I know where you're going with it, yeah.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh. It's about, how?
Eric Rosenbaum: Giving is receiving.
Eric Rosenbaum: And… letting go.
Eric Rosenbaum: is… lightness.
Eric Rosenbaum: Once, when I was a kid, I,
Eric Rosenbaum: I just acted so fast out of instinct. I reached my hand to grab the frying pan that my mom had dropped.
Eric Rosenbaum: She wasn't really my mom, but, you know, the family I was living with.
Eric Rosenbaum: Into the fireplace.
Eric Rosenbaum: And… you know, I've always been kind of quick, so I managed to grab it right by the handle.
Eric Rosenbaum: But,
Eric Rosenbaum: Everybody was kind of afraid and surprised when I held it up, smiling, and gave it back, because… it was burning hot.
Eric Rosenbaum: But I didn't feel it. Nobody understood why. They were a little afraid of me after that, and I left home
Eric Rosenbaum: Just for a day or two, like I would sometimes.
Eric Rosenbaum: And… wandering around, I've… I realized it was the… The summertime that…
Eric Rosenbaum: My body didn't react to the sun… the way it normally did, and I tried.
Eric Rosenbaum: You know.
Eric Rosenbaum: Juggling hot coals, I found I could.
Eric Rosenbaum: But one day… I took off that ring. It's the one I found when I fell through the floor.
Eric Rosenbaum: And it all stopped.
Eric Rosenbaum: I thought maybe… Maybe I should look into this.
Eric Rosenbaum: Before I had a chance to…
Eric Rosenbaum: Wondering if maybe that could be my way out.
Eric Rosenbaum: Maybe I could sell it.
Eric Rosenbaum: Maybe somebody would be amazed.
Eric Rosenbaum: want to learn from me where I found it.
Eric Rosenbaum: It was the Midsummer Festival.
Eric Rosenbaum: Right around then, too, and
Eric Rosenbaum: You know, they love the fireworks.
Eric Rosenbaum: In that town where I grew up, and… Sometimes there's accidents.
Eric Rosenbaum: And, normally.
Eric Rosenbaum: the kids I run this.
Eric Rosenbaum: We just laugh, and… Maybe.
Eric Rosenbaum: Sort through the wreckage, but this night… I saw a man weeping.
Eric Rosenbaum: Before a burning structure.
Eric Rosenbaum: And he was calling out for help because… This kid was in there.
Eric Rosenbaum: And… Something let go inside me, and I,
Eric Rosenbaum: I went to him, and I gave him the ring.
Eric Rosenbaum: I said, look.
Eric Rosenbaum: Look, this will protect you. You can go.
Eric Rosenbaum: You can rescue her.
Eric Rosenbaum: And he went in.
Eric Rosenbaum: And he was not burned.
Eric Rosenbaum: And I felt something that also…
Eric Rosenbaum: Became calm within me.
Eric Rosenbaum: Because I thought maybe… That thing I found, I should find more of those things in that…
Eric Rosenbaum: That was all I would need in life, but…
Eric Rosenbaum: That moment, I realized there was more.
Eric Rosenbaum: I needed both to take and to give.
Eric Rosenbaum: at… I never saw that man again. I don't know if his child… Survived.
Eric Rosenbaum: But I do know that I have a feeling.
Eric Rosenbaum: Of having made a change in the world for the better.
Eric Rosenbaum: But I could only do it by giving something.
Eric Rosenbaum: Instead of holding it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): With the story of the entity…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Thinks back to the other stories its teacher told it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the games that they played together.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the give and take of… imagining possibilities and growing into shapes, where… when the teacher was teaching it how to grow itself into…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Buildings, and to stretch its roots far and wide, that they… that there was an interchange there.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That's lovely, alright. Roll it up.
Eric Rosenbaum: It's, Persuasion check, and I have the inspiration… That's what I got.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh, man. Are you wrong? That's…
Eric Rosenbaum: I rolled a 5 with a plus 3, so that's an 8.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Give her luck?
Eric Rosenbaum: I don't know, I don't think so.
Mike Sackton: Are you… you're… human?
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah…
Mike Sackton: If you're human, you'd have a heroic if you haven't used it yet, because you get whatever you want, Rev.
Eric Rosenbaum: It's not.
Eric Rosenbaum: present on my character sheet, but that doesn't necessarily mean I don't have it.
Mike Sackton: We rested… when did we last rest?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): In the…
Tim Sackton: A couple sessions ago. It was in the temple.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Know that you…
Mike Sackton: I don't think you used Relic, though.
David S. Kong: I don't think you have either.
Mike Sackton: We all forget to tick it when we want rest as humans, because D&D brawn doesn't automatically do it.
Eric Rosenbaum: So what does that let me do?
Mike Sackton: can re-roll.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yes, I will do so.
Eric Rosenbaum: So I just roll… I'll just re-roll the… persuasion…
Eric Rosenbaum: That's a total of 15 that time, that's better.
Mike Sackton: Adribartic?
Eric Rosenbaum: And that's… what's the… how much is the bardic? 86?
Tim Sackton: sex.
Eric Rosenbaum: That's a 5.
Mike Sackton: 20.
Eric Rosenbaum: Awesome.
David S. Kong: Yeah, that was an awesome story, Eric.
Eric Rosenbaum: Thanks.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): cool.
David S. Kong: Kill that.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You guys are doing great, this is not automatically impossible.
Kate Sackton: 18? Has been, you know, giving out her bardic inspiration by drumming along gently with
Kate Sackton: Her colleagues' songs or stories.
Kate Sackton: And now she eats a little bit more…
Kate Sackton: firmly on her hand drum. She wants to…
Kate Sackton: Sing a song, tell a story of… Reflecting back, This, entity's experience.
Kate Sackton: The way everyone can relate.
Kate Sackton: to… memories… and experiences…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: and hopes.
Kate Sackton: Being the same.
Kate Sackton: Shine that light back on how…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Something given isn't gone.
Kate Sackton: So…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Aveen…
Kate Sackton: Does…
Kate Sackton: I sing a song… All the people… Who have told me… They've seen… A meaningful light shining.
Kate Sackton: I've seen…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Hey, Lord.
Kate Sackton: Thinking in endless twilight.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: of…
Kate Sackton: Stars in the sky.
Kate Sackton: I've seen… The moon.
Kate Sackton: Shining so bright.
Kate Sackton: And… Making people think.
Kate Sackton: Of the day that is to come.
Kate Sackton: On the day that was passed, And… a night for dreaming.
Kate Sackton: And the lights twinkle in the sky.
Kate Sackton: the stars.
Kate Sackton: They have a rhythm of their own in the pulse of the twinkle.
Kate Sackton: And when it's daytime and you can't see them, You still know… That particular bright light.
Kate Sackton: of the stars.
Kate Sackton: And when it's… Nighttime, but there's no moon.
Kate Sackton: You still know… That particular radiance.
Kate Sackton: Of being bathed in that.
Kate Sackton: Soft light.
Kate Sackton: And… All of these lights… come to different people, and they mean so much, and they're not gone.
Kate Sackton: When they're not there.
Kate Sackton: And… In the Feywild at Twilight.
Kate Sackton: Or… In the dark of a well.
Kate Sackton: There's always the thought… Of the bright shining.
Kate Sackton: of… The lights that we've seen, The souls that we've met, And the rhythm…
Kate Sackton: Of their movement in our memories.
Kate Sackton: And our hope that we will see them again.
Kate Sackton: And are knowing that they are…
Kate Sackton: And they have been. And they will be.
Kate Sackton: And we see the stars.
Kate Sackton: In the daytime.
Kate Sackton: In our mind.
Kate Sackton: And we see the sun, At night.
Kate Sackton: In our memory.
Kate Sackton: And we look forward to the moon.
Kate Sackton: On the dark nights, when she is not there.
Kate Sackton: And always… As a candle flickers.
Kate Sackton: When a person comes into a room.
Kate Sackton: There's coming, and there's going, and the lights are different, and they're the same.
Kate Sackton: And… The moon will come again.
Kate Sackton: The stars will always be there pulsing.
Kate Sackton: They twinkle.
Kate Sackton: I'm missing…
Kate Sackton: And everything has its place, and its place is to be what it can be.
Kate Sackton: And what it has been.
Kate Sackton: And be shared by everyone.
Kate Sackton: And… Everyone reflects back.
Kate Sackton: And I… We've.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): you give us the results of the roll.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Two things. One is, there's a line in a Wendell Berry poem where he talks about being outdoors during the day, and overhead are the day-blind stars.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And I always love that, it's something almost like Old English about that.
Kate Sackton: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): stars. But the entity… Within itself.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): there's something that's a shifting. It's… it's said, or it's intimated that…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): it lives its entire life simultaneously, that it doesn't experience or understand or have the sense of befores and afters. And there's something in what you're saying that…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Helps it remember that
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Even if it let these things go, it's still having them. It's not a creature that lives in time.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It's still having the moment of having them.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And, alright.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): How'd the persuasion roll go?
Kate Sackton: Mmm…
Kate Sackton: Well, I rolled a 16. Adding my 7 to Persuasion is… 23 plus… The bardic from my…
Kate Sackton: Elven Bartic colleague… Is another 3, so 26.
Mike Sackton: That's, that's, like, more than the rest of us put together, but, you know.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Well, it helps to roll a double-digit number.
Mike Sackton: It does. I mean, it turns out it really does.
David S. Kong: I gotta be a bard.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: So…
Kate Sackton: I'm the handgun.
Tim Sackton: On the ground this whole time, not really listening to the stories.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: And… Beautiful.
Tim Sackton: Looks up as Aveen finishes.
Tim Sackton: Her tail. And you can see that he's, like, kinda…
Tim Sackton: Inflicted or despairing a little bit, like…
Tim Sackton: He's probably never told a story in his life.
Tim Sackton: And…
Tim Sackton: Isn't the sort of person who
Tim Sackton: he's a loner by trade, right?
Tim Sackton: And as he's sitting there, he…
Tim Sackton: Turns and he looks up into the darkness.
Tim Sackton: And even though he has… he left his village under some conflict, with his… with the elders of the village.
Tim Sackton: And he is somewhat reluctant to call on his ancestors for aid.
Tim Sackton: He turns, and he looks, and he says.
Tim Sackton: Well, it doesn't say anything, it says something in lizard language you don't understand, but,
Tim Sackton: But as he does, and I'm using the Lizardfolk Ancestral aid ability to give myself persuasion in, proficiency in persuasion.
Tim Sackton: And flavoring it as the ancestors speaking through him.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, I love it.
Eric Rosenbaum: Word.
Tim Sackton: His voice changes to this sort of gravelly, almost echoey tone.
Tim Sackton: And he turns and he looks…
Tim Sackton: In the direction of the entity, wherever it is, clearly being able to see it or sense it in some manner.
Tim Sackton: And those of you who know Charo don't really recognize him anymore. It's almost as if he's possessed.
Tim Sackton: And he begins speaking, and he says directly to the entity.
Tim Sackton: You want to know how to let something go that you think you cannot.
Tim Sackton: This is the story of the lizardfolk Charo.
Tim Sackton: Who we thought we could not let go.
Tim Sackton: And Billy did.
Tim Sackton: And the voice of Char begins speaking and tells the story of… A young man.
Tim Sackton: Who felt?
Tim Sackton: Trapped in his village.
Tim Sackton: Lizard spoke villages, the ancestor explains to this…
Tim Sackton: entity that presumably doesn't understand them are…
Tim Sackton: Places of abundance where life thrives.
Tim Sackton: But places of order and rigidity, too, where everything must have its place. And the village is like the fish weir that we build on the river that brings food and nutrients and life, but traps everything that swims through it.
Tim Sackton: And the voice continues staying, huh, while many thrive growing into the weave and vines of these nets that make the village strong and whole.
Tim Sackton: Chara was trapped.
Tim Sackton: The net caught him.
Tim Sackton: And we could not let go.
Tim Sackton: We wanted to hold him to ourselves, to keep him in the village.
Tim Sackton: To make him… us.
Tim Sackton: To turn him into the net. Like his brothers and sisters and nest mates and cousins.
Tim Sackton: And he wandered, and we kept pulling him back. And we saw…
Tim Sackton: The net begin to weave around him.
Tim Sackton: Structures of our village begin to… grow over him.
Tim Sackton: encase him, bind him. We were grasping him tightly.
Tim Sackton: But what we did not see until it was almost too late.
Tim Sackton: As there was no longer Charo.
Tim Sackton: We were turning him into something else.
Tim Sackton: It was only by opening our hand.
Tim Sackton: And letting him… Out of the net.
Tim Sackton: Escape the rigidity.
Tim Sackton: strict tourism.
Tim Sackton: the village itself.
Tim Sackton: That he could be who he was.
Tim Sackton: So as you grasp these souls that you love, You destroy them.
Tim Sackton: But it is not too late.
Tim Sackton: Because we learned our lesson. We realized.
Tim Sackton: We had to let him… find himself.
Tim Sackton: And so we opened our hands, we broke the bonds of those nets, and we let him…
Tim Sackton: Blow down the river to where fate took him.
Tim Sackton: And that is how he is here now, and that is what you now can do for yourself.
Tim Sackton: And Chara's eyes open, and he sort of blinks.
Tim Sackton: And looks around, sort of mutters, did I… Did I say something?
David S. Kong: Kato's like, that was really good.
David S. Kong: That's good.
Eric Rosenbaum: You did well, Charo. You did well.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): old.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Yup.
Tim Sackton: That is a…
Tim Sackton: 16, because I also get a plus D4 from the ancestor's aid. Plus, I'm proficient, so that's now…
Audio shared by David S. Kong: 8.
Tim Sackton: plus a D6.
Tim Sackton: That's 20.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: You feel it in your body.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Each of you.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Before you can consciously perceive The rumbling vibration.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The sound that's moving through you, not just your ears, but your whole body, the sound that you can feel in your lungs.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): of something… Like the sound of an earthquake.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The pitch blackness doesn't change. There's nothing that you can see with your eyes.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But at the same time, Like the painting that you stumbled across in the lecture hall.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You can see a patch of darkness which is blacker than everything else.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): A patch of darkness in the shape of a child, standing on almost a hillside of roots and bone.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It opens its hands, and cradled in the palm of its hands.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Is something like a seed pod of a milkweed.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: containing…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Containing a something inside it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Which, no matter how hard you try to remember, in all the years that come.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You can never remember exactly what it looked like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, a hundred tiny seeds blowing away through the air as the child
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Let's go of the hundred souls it held.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And lets them send onward, and they flow.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Straight.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Swift in a direction away from every other direction, going to a home that none of you know, but to which you each will go one day, and they're gone.
Eric Rosenbaum: Hmm.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Hanging in a makeshift backpack.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): A ray opens its mouth and its eyes.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): and says, What? Wha… wha-wh- And then its voice slows.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And it goes still and inert, and you know that whatever powered it is gone, and in fact, whatever powered the whole of the 27th
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): room.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): is… Gone.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the rumbling.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Grows deeper, and at the same time.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The child begins to shift and change in its shape.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And as the house collapses around you, it grows and bursts the prison open from the inside out.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And this, what you see, you DO remember.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You remember, in every one of the worst moments of your life that come in all of the years that follow, this is what you see when you close your eyes. It is…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): An un-thing. Made of bone and bramble and tree roots and mold, shaped something like a dandelion made of darkness seven stories tall.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): In its roots, the size of elephants are alive and writhing like slugs, like pale leeches exposed to the light, terrified, unthinking, reaching through the boundaries of the multiverse like living and clawed things.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the dandelion at the top, this pale sphere, spread out.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): At the end of each of those seeds are the faces of everyone you have ever met, trying to rip themselves free of the horror that they know that they are. A plant whose leaves around the base are tentacles of rot and bone and darkness, which, until recently.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Wrapped themselves around the shimmering spheres of mortal souls which screamed for centuries without ever stopping.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And what you know.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): In the darkness and the nightmare moments in the decades to come are that this thing that you perceive is only the closest approximation your mind can make of what it actually is.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And then it's a child again.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the ruins and remains of the prison.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And of the house, now shaken apart around you as you were sheltered under one of these horror leaves.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Are sliding down the sides of the cliff, and into the ravine, and into the darkness.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The child is sitting at the edge of a low stone well, maybe a foot high above the Cliffside.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Where a doorframe used to be leading into the house.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It shakes the last of the milkweed puffs free from its hand.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And looks at each of you simultaneously.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And you see in it a child, and an adult, and a madman, and a monster, all at once.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And it puts a single finger in front of its lips.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And disappears down the well.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the five of you are left.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): On an empty hillside, In the gathering twilight.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Just as the first stars of evening are beginning to come out.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That's where we'll end, and I… I have a closing… Montage 2.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But before that, I want to give a moment, if there's…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): conversation or business up among the five of you. I don't want to cut it off without… if there's anything that needs…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Saying among the party.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But we are gonna leave you there.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: I don't think there's anything to say.
Eric Rosenbaum: Just so good.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I think from there…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The camera pans up and away from you.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And out towards the horizon where the sun has set?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And then pans back again.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And it's the last of the sunset shining through a high window of an old house.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Onto the bloody and exhausted form of Lord Hulda.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Surrounded by the butchered corpse of the half-dozen mushroom men Aldens, who were his servants. And he drinks a potion, but his wounds don't fully close, and he coughs, and then he coughs again, and he doesn't stop coughing until he does, all at once.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Below the old trees, on the wild edges of the Duchy of Tellim, it's always dusk.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And in that twilight, the pale mushroom children of the thirst walk without sleeping or dreaming or hungering, and they flee from fire and iron, and they make new siblings out of anyone they find.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And they search in those woods, always, obsessively, for the hidden door that will bring them back home to their parent again.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): In a room filled with glass tanks of fungus, Growing on severed limbs.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Just as you feel the first rumbles start to vibrate.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Through, just as you can see the glass tanks shaking and the houses destroyed.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): A body in the shape of a dwarven woman, but made from fungi and lichens of every possible description, sits up and looks, for a long moment, at the lifeless corpse which once held the soul now encased in its own fungal golem flesh.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And as the room around her shakes, as pieces of the ceiling begin to fall to the floor, Calypses, now wizard head of Erythramos lamparum in a golem body, consults a book filled with long lists of six-digit numbers and blinks out of sight.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Camera pulls back.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And it's a quiet, thatched cottage by the side of a road which runs parallel exactly to the sunset, and a tigerman is stowing in his bag the polished sphere of crystal through which he watched a golem plane shift out of the Feywild.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And he draws thoughtfully from his pipe.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: and size.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And at the corners of his mouth, a sly smile creeps across the massive tiger face.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It is no time. It is not time, it is outside of time, in the black nothingness beyond the universe, where the black stars do not shine, and an un-thing that is sometimes a child, and sometimes a monster.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): can once again see the complete and unambiguous shape of all of its own possibilities. Its past, its present, its future, all at once, unhidden, always moving, never changing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And in that place, which is not a place.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It doesn't think of the soul horde it kept.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But of the teacher who found it as a lost child and loved it into speech.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And finally… Finally.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Under a twilight sky, Wide green lawns rise from the river to a beautiful manor house.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Where a party has finished.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The paper lanterns hanging on long lines are all extinguished, and the grounds are silent, and the partygoers have departed.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And in the upper room of the dark house, the Lord of the ended revel looks out a high window.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Toward the place where the sun has set.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Thinking of the child he befriended.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Just before his party began.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And 5 travelers.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Standing above a ravine, Look to each other.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And began to think on the way back home again.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That's where we'll live in.
Eric Rosenbaum: Spectacular.
Eric Rosenbaum: Damn.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): This was really fun, y'all. Thank you.
Kate Sackton: Hey, wild.
Mike Sackton: No, that's fun.
David S. Kong: Wow.
Mike Sackton: Yep.
David S. Kong: Okay.
David S. Kong: Schwartz. So, what?
David S. Kong: What's going on with the guy?
Eric Rosenbaum: Excellent.
David S. Kong: How are we doing?
Mike Sackton: All of our own theories as to what was going on.
David S. Kong: Yeah, I would love it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I would love that so much, actually.
David S. Kong: Let's do our own theories, and I want to hear what Schwartz thinks.
Mike Sackton: Schwartz is.
Mike Sackton: I mean, who knows? Schwartz doesn't necessarily know what was going on, right?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I… anything I do, actually.
Eric Rosenbaum: good,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I had to… I had to write up the whole thing in order not to mess up the pieces along the way, so I'm… Right. I have a definitive story, but I'm really curious for yours.
Tim Sackton: Arm Realm entity crashed into Telgo.
David S. Kong: What entity?
Tim Sackton: Far realm. Far realm.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah, this…
Tim Sackton: Lian Realm.
Eric Rosenbaum: And there's a way to go down…
Eric Rosenbaum: The well to it, which is kind of interesting, too.
Eric Rosenbaum: But…
Tim Sackton: Started growing houses, learned what houses and dreams and people were, started growing houses.
Eric Rosenbaum: From this Feylord who helped it.
Eric Rosenbaum: learn what… Yeah, the Lord was the teacher.
Audio shared by David S. Kong: Right?
Eric Rosenbaum: That's the But then… But then he had to… Trap it.
Eric Rosenbaum: For some reason.
Tim Sackton: No, the rhythm…
Mike Sackton: They're remiss, man.
Tim Sackton: Bancroine Society.
Mike Sackton: Crap.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh, they trapped it.
Mike Sackton: And they started feeding it souls to do things, and it liked the souls.
Mike Sackton: And so it kept.
Tim Sackton: Well, it might have been collecting souls before it was trapped, we don't really know.
David S. Kong: Or was it, like, an opium type of thing, and, like, once they trapped it, they, like, they, like, got it hooked on drugs, got it hooked on soul drugs?
Mike Sackton: I… I was not… I mean, Far Realms was probably… is a plausible… it wasn't clear to me that this wasn't just some sort of thing creature in some strange sense. Like, it wasn't clear… I didn't… I didn't… I wouldn't have started with Far Realms, although…
Tim Sackton: Well, you missed the little Easter egg about the books.
Eric Rosenbaum: Resilience.
Mike Sackton: I actually looked up the book, and I saw it was about the fire realms, but I didn't put two and two together.
Mike Sackton: The far round makes more canonical sense than the Feywild, for sure.
Mike Sackton: I just hadn't picked up on that.
Tim Sackton: No, I knew it was far around from, like, session 3 or something. The first time we got the prisoner.
Tim Sackton: One of the journals was clearly Far Rome.
David S. Kong: What are the Far Realms?
Tim Sackton: And it learned about… it called the souls Dreamers… called them dreamers because of the Feylord's interpretation of the plane of souls as an echo. Schwartz has been… I know what's going on.
Mike Sackton: Schwartz has been mined every bit of it.
Tim Sackton: cosmology section of Taldarverse, which is incredibly satisfying.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That's clear.
Tim Sackton: So, there is one theory among human scholars that the Fae think the dream world is actually real, and the plane of souls is an echo of the dream world. So, the Fae lord is a believer of that theory.
Tim Sackton: called. Sold.
Tim Sackton: Dreams, slash… People with souls, dreamers.
David S. Kong: Mmm…
Mike Sackton: break.
Mike Sackton: But, so, Endlessly Ending was… Right.
Mike Sackton: was found with this guy. I guess it's not very clear what… this Twilight Kingdom was before.
Mike Sackton: or after.
Tim Sackton: Well, there were many hazards.
Mike Sackton: I guess there's many houses.
Tim Sackton: But…
Mike Sackton: once…
Tim Sackton: Wednesday's really good.
Eric Rosenbaum: eaten.
Tim Sackton: We know at least one other one turned into… Corrupted coral madness.
Tim Sackton: But once the… Once the, the erythrovirus…
Tim Sackton: They can never remember their name.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Originally, now…
Tim Sackton: the challenge I leave for you guys…
Tim Sackton: It is much harder to remember names as a player than a DM.
Kate Sackton: No.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So much harder.
Tim Sackton: But I can just look it up.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): earlier for the far realms being, like, the places outside the universe. Like, there's the multiverse of all the planes, and then there's whatever isn't within the totality of creation, and, like, those are the far… like, outside of the universe.
Eric Rosenbaum: But what's outside of that?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You… y'all missed the opportunity to ask this dude.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Who would have known?
Eric Rosenbaum: True.
Tim Sackton: Mom.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Sure, my thinking.
Kate Sackton: Excuse me.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Eric, is that… my headcanon is that…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): When he talks about a dark place with dark stars, that each of the dark stars within the far realms are themselves other somethings.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah, huh?
Mike Sackton: I mean, the firearms are canonically plural, there's not just one. Right.
Eric Rosenbaum: Right.
Mike Sackton: Right.
Eric Rosenbaum: Cool, cool.
Mike Sackton: And they're not all necessarily evil or bad, they're just aliens.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, exactly. This is,
Tim Sackton: Nicole Ardwin's theory of the University of Toland that good and evil are not the right metrics to judge such alien realms, in her seminal work, The Exposition of the Alien Mind, she argued that some of the far realms that are home to beings who, if they could only be communicated, could bring much new knowledge to the world.
Eric Rosenbaum: Wait, I think she'd have…
Mike Sackton: When was that person writing? When did she write? Does that book have a date?
Kate Sackton: 13.
Tim Sackton: You'll have to.
Tim Sackton: You'll have to look at the…
Mike Sackton: At the store.
Tim Sackton: Intellectual history of… No, it's in… it's in Telgarverse, the Intellectual History of Cosmology in Telgar.
Mike Sackton: No, I'm wondering if that particular book had a date.
David S. Kong: Tim, Tim, did you write that?
Tim Sackton: Yeah.
David S. Kong: That text, that you just.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yep. Yeah.
Tim Sackton: I told you, Schwartz is mining the deep cuts from Tago purse.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh, good.
Tim Sackton: In the 1600s.
Mike Sackton: He died on the back.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I definitely do not, like, it's definitely not canonical, but I like the idea that over the years, it's possible many of those people passed through the party and, like, had a casual conversation and heard, you know, secondhand about bits or pieces.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, no, it's perfect, because all of them disappeared.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Which…
Mike Sackton: people.
Tim Sackton: The fact that she never returned from a research expedition to the marches of Enford have kept her work marginal.
Mike Sackton: Wow, but wait, wait, wait, you can't use that for this, because I'm going to use that for my campaign.
Tim Sackton: Okay.
Mike Sackton: Let Marches of Edward in there, because I have a Far Realms thing planned in my game. But it could be a different,
Mike Sackton: It's nowhere close… Martian Bankford is nowhere close to you. You put that Easter egg in for me, because I told you to.
Tim Sackton: Okay.
Mike Sackton: But, there's other Fire Realms people.
Tim Sackton: The Ardrum Deepseeker, who wrote the other far-round book I invented, also mysteriously vanished.
Tim Sackton: So maybe he was one of the dwarves. Anyway, the Anthropomoros lampirum
Tim Sackton: Found out about this entity somehow, probably because…
Tim Sackton: Its roots were causing planar weirdness that they detected. Came to the…
Tim Sackton: Feywild, and was like, oh, cool, we can power a magical laboratory with this thing, Souls.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): First, actually.
Tim Sackton: Or something like that.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yes, but before that, the first use for it was they could feed their enemies to it, so they couldn't be resurrected or communicated with.
Tim Sackton: Right, that I missed. That was a very subtle hint somewhere.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That was a deep cut, but soon after that, this… the other person…
Mike Sackton: picked up on that, it's eating their souls, so they can't be resurrected. That was the one… whole thing he was upset about.
Tim Sackton: So then they built the 27th house, and in order to power it, they needed mortals walking through it, so they convinced…
Tim Sackton: tricked the Feylord into the deal.
Tim Sackton: Which then…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): When the order was still active, they didn't need the Feylord, because they were there once.
Tim Sackton: They were there, but when they were… the last of the last leader of the order was like, all my people are gone, that's why it was… that's why there was nobody in the house, because the order had left.
David S. Kong: What happened to the order? Why did they leave? The house?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Apollyon disbanded them, because they're… because they were powerful. Because they had their own resources, because whatever…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You think it does?
David S. Kong: them.
Tim Sackton: This is… did I send you, Schwartz to…
Tim Sackton: history at… I sent you that history at the end of.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah.
Tim Sackton: Telco, right? Okay, yeah, yeah. This is not on… I should put this on Telgoverse.
Tim Sackton: This is a deep cut that you couldn't have picked up on… nobody else could have picked up on because of the fact that it's not public.
Mike Sackton: which…
Mike Sackton: one.
Tim Sackton: My timeline for the end of…
Tim Sackton: Drancor… for the fall of the Drancorian Empire that I wrote for the circular… for the Apollyon arc, which includes when he, like, consolidated power and…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And you all didn't get the exact date, but you did, from Menisthees, get the,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Get the story of the order being disbanded.
Tim Sackton: Right.
Mike Sackton: Wait, that's not in… you have a timeline?
Mike Sackton: Is it not in… Is it…
Tim Sackton: No, no, it's in my… it's in my Dunmari Frontier DM notes, which are not… That way.
Mike Sackton: Sure, it's sick.
Tim Sackton: I… they're too disorganized.
Tim Sackton: I forget the exact… I think it was, like, 10.30…
Tim Sackton: One, or something like that. Anyway, I sent Schwartz the thing, and we worked out the timeline, so that I sort of knew from
Tim Sackton: So then, the order was disbanded. They had to establish a new way to keep the prison moving. So that's when they made the… they tricked the Faey lord into sending mortals.
Tim Sackton: And then…
David S. Kong: What's the deal with.
Tim Sackton: From the order's point of view, that brings us to today, basically.
David S. Kong: What the hell was going on with Holga in the fourth iteration, that whole thing?
David S. Kong: Like, like, the.
Tim Sackton: Bears.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
David S. Kong: Fourth edition of The Matrix.
Tim Sackton: The… in order to… so people could leave the prison room.
Tim Sackton: remember, only one-third… Eric wasn't there for this, but one-third of the people turned into mushrooms, and…
Tim Sackton: exited back into the manor. The others left.
Tim Sackton: But they left to random times, because the.
Eric Rosenbaum: Central.
Tim Sackton: of the room.
Tim Sackton: the central room in the prison was always at a rant… pointing to a random time back in Telgar. But… some of them presumably attempted to…
Tim Sackton: Either from conversation with the entity.
Tim Sackton: the first, or out of their own volition. That, I think, is… was not clear from what we were able to learn.
Tim Sackton: Tried to figure out ways to…
Tim Sackton: get people back to free the entity, or at least interact with the entity, and Holda…
Tim Sackton: showed up in 1351 Sambara. Sambara didn't exist at that point, actually.
Tim Sackton: But the ducks didn't tell him dead.
Tim Sackton: Tembarn as a language existed. He…
Tim Sackton: somehow, and this I didn't quite figure out.
Tim Sackton: own this land, or… I don't know how he got the deed originally, but he wrote a deed and gave it to an elf, because elves are long-lived.
Tim Sackton: So that they could then pass it on to himself, As a younger man, before he…
Tim Sackton: like, in the time loop, right? Before himself in.
Eric Rosenbaum: 1715.
Eric Rosenbaum: He went in.
Tim Sackton: to the Feywild.
Eric Rosenbaum: He wrote his own… like…
Tim Sackton: Presumably… He could leave the party because he had already gone into the house in another timeline.
Tim Sackton: I don't know if that was intentional, Schwartz.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): There's some… there's some ambiguity to that one.
Tim Sackton: So, the deed was written by him.
Mike Sackton: Right.
Tim Sackton: In 1752, or whenever.
Tim Sackton: Sorry, 1352. Yeah.
Tim Sackton: Given to an elf to hold onto, and then passed to him when he was born again.
David S. Kong: And that's why… that's why the deed is so fucking old. Like, when it's written…
Mike Sackton: That's why it didn't… it didn't… why not, right? That's why it was… that's why it was…
Eric Rosenbaum: outage.
Mike Sackton: I mean, I mean, the, the…
Tim Sackton: Because he had learned modern Sambara, Sambarin in 1750, or 1750.
Eric Rosenbaum: 1940.
Tim Sackton: So the deed that was 400 years old should have been written in a more archaic language, but wasn't. Right. Because it, in fact, was a time traveler who broke it. Right.
Mike Sackton: And in practice, actually, probably also did not use the correct
Mike Sackton: anybody who knew the details… I've actually made up a surprising amount of the.
Tim Sackton: Right, it would have been…
Mike Sackton: It would have been, like, it would have been, like.
Tim Sackton: in…
Mike Sackton: archaic, and it's like, you know, it says this is in the court of the Duchy of Tellum, and doesn't mention Sambara, when it should have been in the court of Sambara, or something like that. Like, it would have had the wrong…
Tim Sackton: No, it was the… no, because it was…
Mike Sackton: No, no, it was written in the court.
Mike Sackton: But that savar didn't actually exist, if you know yet.
Tim Sackton: Didn't exist 400 years ago, so the legal language of the deed would have been wrong for 1752.
David S. Kong: Alright, Troy.
Tim Sackton: The other three we didn't know about, they were just other 3 parties that we just never learned.
Tim Sackton: Did I miss anything? I don't know.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'll fill in some holes. But I like to think, although I don't know if this works with your
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): sense of it, Tim, is that he gave the deed to the Philosopher's Guild in exchange for one of the clocks that he had taken from the house, as payment for them fulfilling it 400 years later. I don't know if that's the sort of thing they do, but…
Tim Sackton: Definitely not the Philosopher's Guild.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Some magical society or another. Anyways…
Tim Sackton: I mean, somebody could have, but the Philosopher's Guild would not… would never do an errand for anybody.
Eric Rosenbaum: Mmm.
Tim Sackton: They would never stoop so low as to be a courier.
Eric Rosenbaum: Maybe there's some…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You're… you're confirming they're not a Drancorian secret society.
Mike Sackton: Well, we do that.
Tim Sackton: You knew they weren't… I mean, they're… No, I would say.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, yeah.
David S. Kong: Short story.
Tim Sackton: learn.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That's the… that's the key pieces of it. You know, going back to the beginning again,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, this seed or spore or little piece of an entity from outside of the universe
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): drifts through.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): There's part of me that likes to think that in the downfall wars, there were things that poked holes in the fabric of the universe that never got resolved.
Tim Sackton: Canonautical, in fact.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And it found its way through one of these holes and planted on the hillside. And…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The Feylord, which was the next neighbor from down the road,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, my sensibility about this guy is that…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): like, he… it doesn't matter to him that this is a thing from beyond the universe. Like, he doesn't… he doesn't think about that experience, or this entity, or the danger it poses, or the fact that it could eat souls, like, just none of those things are relevant to him and who he is.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): because he is so entirely in control of his own dominion, or he believes that he is. Like, he doesn't feel any sense of threat or danger, like, whatsoever. So he just treats it like, oh, this is a weird thing, let's… let's…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): let's teach it how to grow houses, and create, and about how time works, and then he's gotta go off to start his own party.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I think the first… in the story that it told you today.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): the first couple of souls that it ate were members of the Earthra Muslim harem who were tracing
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Tracing back the roots that it had grown,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I like to think that it just didn't understand that the different planes were different things, and so it didn't understand why its roots wouldn't just cross planes.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And so they followed it back, and got eaten, and the next one got eaten, and so they came in force, and they put it inside the prison.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And then discovered that it could grow its way out of the prison.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Because it lives its entire life simultaneously, if it can predict what's going to happen.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It can grow its way… it can anticipate that and grow its way out.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So they realized that they would have to keep it constantly moving to sort of prune the roots that were growing out of it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Hmm.
Eric Rosenbaum: It's a concert.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): be trimming those, otherwise it would grow, keep on growing across the plains.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And this one particular… According to Edric, evil, but, you know, all progress involved sacrifice. Wizard…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): figured out how to harness the, sort of, potential energy of souls trying to get back to the plane of souls, and to tap into that as a power source, and built the house out of that.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And who knows what other evil things across the universe are powered by that.
Tim Sackton: And this is basically what, the…
Tim Sackton: Now I'm forgetting the name of the things I made up.
Eric Rosenbaum: The mirror of soul trapping.
Eric Rosenbaum: You could use… No, not the Marathon.
Tim Sackton: I think the… the… the…
Mike Sackton: Remember the.
Tim Sackton: fort… the elemental forge, that was, like, a trapped air element… trapped powerful being of the… from the air elemental. It's basically the same mechanism that…
Mike Sackton: But was it also a polyod prison, kind of a similar mechanism?
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yep.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, that was… I asked for the…
Tim Sackton: Was a similar mechanism, except it was the reverse, the soles getting out.
Tim Sackton: We're actually destroying the prison, not create…
Tim Sackton: Yes, the energy of the sun.
Eric Rosenbaum: How are you?
Tim Sackton: was destroying the prison. Yeah.
Mike Sackton: It was just that the energy was directed into something different for the.
Tim Sackton: Yes.
Mike Sackton: automatically.
Tim Sackton: I don't know if you have more to fill in, Schwartz, but I just want to say, I…
Tim Sackton: I, like, just deeply love how you… Made up your own stuff?
Tim Sackton: But it just somehow totally feels completely Talgar-y.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, this is such a high praise, thank you!
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I was trying hard not to mess up your world.
Tim Sackton: No, it's… well, I just… it's great. I love other people making up stuff, but when you're players, you're much more reluctant to invent stuff.
Tim Sackton: But, like, everything just… it… it has the vibe completely right, but it adds new, unique stuff, which is…
Tim Sackton: Great.
Mike Sackton: Do you envision Endlessly Ending as… is this all his realm? Like, is he the lord of this realm, or is he, like, one of many in this, like…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): He's one of many, so the,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, it's so funny. This is in my notes that I read over before every session, but I never actually said, like, so the Twilight Kingdoms…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Where you were, are one of the interstitial spaces where, rather than, like, a big lord ruling all of it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You know, a dozen dozen houses, and some of them are like his were, and some of them are just little thatched cottages by the side of the road, or a tent, or a little castle, and the domain of each of those
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): like, the people who rule each of the… who run each of those, are no less powerful than a Theylord is in their domain, it's just that it's very small.
Mike Sackton: I'm like…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The space that you rule is, like, the living room and the kitchen. Or…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You know, in Endlessly Endings case, a little bit more, yeah.
Tim Sackton: Though I have it set up in Talgar verses, Lord Endlessly Ending is the Lord of Lord Endlessly Ending's manner.
Tim Sackton: Which is located in Twilight Kingdom, but Twilight Kingdom does not, in fact, have a lord. Which I didn't actually discuss with Schwartz, I just…
Tim Sackton: Like…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): All of this is correct, yeah.
Tim Sackton: intuitive, but I think that's basically correct.
David S. Kong: works with me.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): fairness, he no longer is Lord Endless Ending.
Mike Sackton: That was the Lord.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): ended rebel who lives in his manor.
David S. Kong: Yeah, the party ended. Schwartz said, what was the deal with the four iterations? Like, the fourth… this is the fourth time?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, oh, yeah. So, okay. So, alright, so the order dissolves, the ending gets tricked to sending people, the souls are the motive power that moves it, but the people, you know, spinning the thing are what keeps the entity from being able to see into the future. And at a certain point.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): These different aspects of the entity all Begin to exist
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): with more of themselves in superposition with each other. So there's the child version, the door that you walked through, but then there's also the, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I mean, there's the, like, long-term addict version, like, the one who has been doing nothing but is… is having,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Someone described addiction to me once, that regardless of the drug and regardless of the person, it is the same story for every single addict. It's fun, and then it's fun with problems, and then it's only problems. And so, like, that is… those are the three aspects. Like, the child, actually, before even finding souls, but then…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Fun with problems is, like, the young adult version who's creating and growing houses and making things, and then only problems. And at some point along the way.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): one of those two entities, and I don't… I'm not sure which it is.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): starts to say, like, I don't actually like this. I actually am in a prison right now. I think it's the third one. I think it's the only problems. Starts to realize, wait a minute, this is not a playhouse, this is a prison, I'm trapped, I need to get free. And when it does that.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It starts… for the people who are coming in, it starts
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): to NOT take their souls, but inst… often, sometimes, but instead to sort of commission them to play, because it can see their whole past and future, like, to play on their desires and drives, and send them out in the world, to try to go break the promise that.
David S. Kong: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): the Lord has made.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And so…
David S. Kong: Wait, wait, sorry, sorry, sorry, just to break the promise so that there will be no more souls that get sent to the house, and then the power will stop, and then…
Tim Sackton: So…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So, so, though, if that had been successful.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): What would have happened is, Endless Landing would have stopped sending souls, the prison would have fallen apart.
David S. Kong: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And it would have become its entity form, like its horror form.
Eric Rosenbaum: I'm growing in…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Wild and expanding back across dimensions.
David S. Kong: Why would it become a spore form?
Eric Rosenbaum: Because they would have been free from the prison.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Because…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Because there would have been no one there to tell it a story about why it shouldn't be.
David S. Kong: Huh.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, because I think on some level, because that IS what the thing is. Like, this is, like, this is… this is not a benign cosmic child.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): this is a cosmic horror. This is something unfathomable and utterly alien, and so far beyond good and evil that life itself has no meaning to it. Like…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And actually, like, from that…
Eric Rosenbaum: Bleeding dandelion, yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And this is the thing, from that perspective, that's why Thelestria cared so much about keeping the prison going. Like, that's why Ministheus was so dedicated to the order.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Even though there were terrible things that it was doing, was because they grasped, like, what the threat was from these cosmic entities.
Tim Sackton: So this is my one question.
Tim Sackton: Charo, I think, very str… I mean, happy to have been pushed by…
Tim Sackton: Plato mostly, I guess, an Edric, convinced that the prisoner was good.
Tim Sackton: in the last session, Charo really basically wanted to take the key back to Lord of the Endlessly ending.
Tim Sackton: But I don't know what would have hopped, like… What would have happened?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So, I prepped for 3 categories of possibilities of what you all might do.
Eric Rosenbaum: Wow.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And one of them was convincing the prisoner to let go of the souls, and in convincing it, you know, to interact with the child and sort of get them sent back home again.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): One of the possible outcomes seemed to be that you could have…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): First, avoided the entire experience with a time loop of your own.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So, I could imagine a scenario, maybe a more selfish party.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): would have gone back to 1351,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Killed Hulda on the road, and happily gone about your lives in 1351.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): with no risk to anyone. Like, that's a… That's a possible outcome.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Another way to avoid the entire experience is
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): If you had waited long enough, or if you had sort of proffered to me the idea of waiting for the next mortal to come into the house and start moving through the rooms.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Then you could have had different times to jump into.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): As they were pushing it through time. And so another possibility is that you go just a few years in the past and intercept an earlier version of yourselves, and prevent yourselves just from taking the job at all in the first place, and go on about your lives on that timeline.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And another possibility was that you went back early enough to prevent… to warn Lord Ending about Thelestria and stop him from making the agreement in the first place.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And another possibility was that you went back early enough To intercept the child
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): before or after it had met Lord Ending, but before it took its first soul and convinced it to go back through to its home then?
David S. Kong: So, how would we have known to… how would we have been able to do any of the time traveling?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So…
Eric Rosenbaum: Well… Yeah, we had some clues.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): strike zero.
David S. Kong: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Lord Ending has to send another mortal through the house, and when the mortal starts moving through the house.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): as they step into the rings which control time, the time inside the chamber jumps, and you would know that because the clock that Tarek has would start jumping.
David S. Kong: Yeah, yeah. But then, to get out of the house and into that time, how would we.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You go… Oh, you go out through the… Correct.
Mike Sackton: No, it's weird.
Tim Sackton: There is a ton…
Mike Sackton: No, no, we see it.
David S. Kong: In the 27th room, we go to the end of the tunnel.
Mike Sackton: Yeah, there was a tunnel, it was just gonna be 13, whatever, and we were like, let's not go. Charla was like, let's just go to the tunnel, what are we doing here? Just leave.
David S. Kong: Right.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the tunnel would have popped you right back out on the cliff, and you could have gone out the door you came in, because it wasn't closed.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Until 1752 or whatever.
Mike Sackton: Right.
Eric Rosenbaum: Right.
David S. Kong: We could have gone back to the house, back to the dandelion house, and then out that door.
Kate Sackton: Right.
Eric Rosenbaum: So all of the time travel games… I feel like… Yeah.
Mike Sackton: I didn't… it didn't really…
Eric Rosenbaum: It didn't become evident until the end.
Mike Sackton: Do any of the time travel games.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): No, no, no, totally, and I… we didn't…
Tim Sackton: So, no, but my…
Kate Sackton: Make it clear that if we died in the past, we didn't… failed to…
Kate Sackton: the time travel games did occur to me because you made it clear that Holda had died in the past, but still was born at his normal time and still had his normal life. So, like, I wasn't worried about.
Eric Rosenbaum: Wait, when was that clear?
Kate Sackton: Whoa.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): We'll get to that, we'll get to that one in a minute.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): There's… I mean, all time travel breaks down if you look too closely at it, but I hope I was consistent.
Kate Sackton: It was consistent.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I think also those didn't occur to you because you are good people and wanted to do, like, the right thing. And especially once Edric was like, no, this will not stand.
Mike Sackton: Like… Right.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): All of the methods of… all of the, like, avoidance scenario, sort of.
Tim Sackton: So, the most likely alternative scenario, in my mind, was…
Tim Sackton: we like Lord the Endlessly Ending. Yeah. I kind of felt sorry for him. Let's help him break the deal.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yes, so, Lord Ending wanted to break the key in order to free the prisoner.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Because he discerned, this being his neighbor right down the road, he had watched what had happened, but been unable to affect it because he was in the middle of a party. He's hosting a party. He's not allowed to leave his party because he's the host.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So if he could break the key and free the prisoner.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): then he would be released from his promise, then his party could end, then he could go help the child get back home again. So my thought was, in any of the scenarios where you're looping back.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): in time, one way or another, and going to Lord Ending to convince him to break the key, like, you could imagine a possibility that whatever year you come out at, you just run right back in again. You literally walk down the road to the party in progress, and have that conversation with Lord Ending.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Convince him to break the key, and then he would… At least to know.
Tim Sackton: So, I was under the impression…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You that you had to convince the child to go home again.
Tim Sackton: Right, but there wasn't any time loop involved there, because we could have just taken the key out of the door.
David S. Kong: I'm just gonna say, yeah, what if we had just not gone in the.
Tim Sackton: Drew.
David S. Kong: Taking the keys.
Tim Sackton: Not in the room at all, taking the key out of the door, walked back through the manor, unlocked the front door, walked to Lord Endlessly Ending's party, and given him the key. That's what he wanted us to do.
David S. Kong: We, we almost did.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): No, no, yeah.
David S. Kong: What would happen?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You're exactly correct about the time loop in that one. So in that scenario, it's the same thing I just described. He breaks the key, the prison comes apart, you have to convince the child. The other scenario I was thinking of, though, is you go into the central prison, and then change your mind, and say, oh shit, we really should have gotten that key.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): At which point, you leave the prison.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And it doesn't matter what… from the perspective of Lord Ending, it does not matter what year you leave the prison.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): as long as it's after the agreement that he's made. As long as it's after his party has started ending.
Tim Sackton: But I don't think… I think once we… I think it was pretty unlikely that we were gonna go back in time, not… I think not… at least from Child's perspective, not because…
Tim Sackton: Of selfishness, just because… That's all… that's, like, even more scary than talking to some weird child, is, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So I agree that it was really unlikely, but I also imagine a scenario in which you as players thought.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Time travel, fuck yeah, let's do this!
Tim Sackton: Yeah.
David S. Kong: Oh, okay.
David S. Kong: I totally would have done that, like, I think… I think Kato would have been…
David S. Kong: But some of the other…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): There was one of you as players in particular I was thinking of, Kong.
Tim Sackton: That has… yeah.
David S. Kong: But wait, Schwartz. The other thing, though, is like, okay, wait.
David S. Kong: because when we went into the room, remember, it's like, we had to choose, like, which one we… Right. And so, like, because we chose the child, I felt like that, like, lent itself more to this, like, oh, let's help, let's, you know, it's like, but if we had gone into the addict room.
David S. Kong: You know what I mean? Like, I don't know if it would have been…
Eric Rosenbaum: From, from a.
David S. Kong: From a player perspective, like, would we have then encountered, like, something way scarier and meaner, and then been more like, oh, fuck, like, fuck this shit, and then…
David S. Kong: you know, done something else, I don't know.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So… Like, I wouldn't actually…
David S. Kong: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): In part, I deliberately made you choose the door at the end of the session in order to only have to prep the door that you…
David S. Kong: Got it, got it, got it, got it. So you don't even know what we would have done had we pecked the…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I mean, I think…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): the three stories that I told you in this session would still have been the three stories
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): in any scenario, because, like, those were the missing pieces that you needed to get. That…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): He came out of a well, and was happy and a child.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): that they trapped him inside of a house, and fed him souls, and the time loop of where Hulda came from, because that thread needed to close.
David S. Kong: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I think, like, In some ways, the addict would have been the second easier one, Because…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm imagining that stage in its life as both, like, profoundly addicted to these souls, but wanting to stop and being unable to?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And so, like…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): In that lens, like, the dynamic would have been different, but it still would have been open to hearing the stories, like, to sort of being persuaded, convinced.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): like… The fun with problems one, I'm not… I'm not totally sure how that would have played out.
David S. Kong: Okay, Schwartz, I have a question since I, you know, I gotta DM the next, the next things. First of all, this is fucking amazing. It was so, so good. Did you, like…
David S. Kong: like, what did you, like, architect in the beginning? Like, did you know, like, what did you create, and then what was it like you were doing session by session? Do you know what I mean? Like, what's, like, just meta for a second? I'm so curious how you…
Eric Rosenbaum: I wonder about that kind of thing as well. Like, what's emergent versus planned, yeah.
David S. Kong: Yeah, yeah, there you go. Yeah, but also, yeah, just, like, what did you arc and pencil out versus, like, you know?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So, like,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): starting back over the winter when I knew I was doing this, I started leaving, like, really long…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Train of Consciousness transcribed voice notes for myself.
David S. Kong: I'm like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Especially, like, just after I had had coffee in the morning, and I was like, and then this thing, and it's a Rubik's Cube, and they're going through time, and it all happens at once!
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I love that. Then, after several pages of that, like, I… when it actually came time to set down and do the thing, like, I went back through all of the notes and said, like, yes, yes, yes, no, this, that.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And… I think for me, like, I was trying to find… when I started out.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I wanted to do a couple of things, which may or may not have worked, and may or may not work in this sort of a game. And one was, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The first idea I had was.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I wanted an adventure that was just a continual process of pulling the rug out from under you. It's one of the things that really is enjoyable as a DM
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): fucking with you. Making you think one thing, and then going in the other direction with it, but, like, constructing that plausibly enough that it really seems like that is the thing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And so, like, that was the… Originally.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): There was a prisoner at the center who actually was a monster, and so you were going in to nobly free it,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And, you know, the turn there is, no, no, no, no, this is a thing that needs to be locked up.
Eric Rosenbaum: Hmm.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, that was one of the pieces that changed over the course of the game. I just felt like that…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That feels less interesting than, like, a sympathetic
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Prisoner that looks like a monster is more interesting than the reverse.
Eric Rosenbaum: I like that, yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And then I also think, like… something…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You should stop me at some point, because, like, talking about writing process is one of my favorite things.
David S. Kong: No, I'm super… I mean.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Bye.
Mike Sackton: I'm gonna have to go to bed shortly.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Hell yeah.
Mike Sackton: I am interested as well, but… but I'm only gonna last another 10 minutes, probably, so…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But, like, I think, like, the key thing for me was…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Somewhere early on in the process, realizing, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I can't… I can't run the game, and I can't put the story together like Tim does. And we had just come off mics too recently, and I was like, oh, I don't… I don't actually know how to do a game the way that either of them did that game.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): and so, especially after the third session of the really, like, annoying, endless
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): puzzle rooms, it was like, wait a minute, like, that's not what I do. I am a writer. Like, I write stories every week.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): years and years and years, like, how do I lean into, like, that?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): as the thing that I'm really good at, and bring that into the game, rather than trying to run the game like someone else would run the game.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And like that… I feel like it made for a really different sort of experience, where I had…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, for each of the sessions that followed.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And actually, for the ones before it, too.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): like, I had… here's a 500-word thing that the…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): that is, like, Hulda's monologue in the first session, or, Lord… or the Rakshasa's story about the, about the deal that was struck.
Tim Sackton: If you look on TagOptVerse, you'll find many of these captured as audio highlights.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): How good is that?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And for me, it was like, what is the nugget, what's the thing at the center of each of the sessions?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And for me, that thing at the center was sort of like a monologue or a story or something. And then, what am I building out around that?
David S. Kong: So all of the, all of the, like, descriptions in those scenes, that was, like… so you, you wrote those first, like, like, before each session, or…
David S. Kong: Like, the ending of this one was, like, sick, like, that whole… I mean, there was a bunch of.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, yeah, yeah.
David S. Kong: Yeah. Yes.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So, like, the way that I think about that, too, is, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The way that I think about writing sermons is, like, what are… what are the story beats? Like, in 2,000 words, in…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): 18 or 20 minutes.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You can do, like, 4 things.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, 20 minutes is no time at all. It's so incredibly short.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And so… when I go to write in that way, it's like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): what are the beats? Like, what's the center of…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): four sections. Like, it's a text and a commentary, it's a poetry, it's a story, it's a something. And then, like, for me, once I know what those beats are, it's like,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I don't actually know how this works, but it's like having a fake book. It's like, here are the changes, and then I can feel… once I know what the changes are.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I can write it, or I can improvise it, but I know where it's going.
David S. Kong: I think my metaphor for this is like, it's like telling a joke. It's like, you know, you know what the setup is, you know what the punchline is, you tell the joke differently every single time, but you know the whole arc and what those key
David S. Kong: You know.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Exactly.
David S. Kong: Togar, yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And then I think also, like, the…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I… I found ways to do it differently later on, but, like, What are the…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): what's, like, the DM point-of-view character who's with the party, and how do I use them.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Nudge in one direction or another.
David S. Kong: Totally, yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Nudging too much or not enough, or…
Eric Rosenbaum: That's an important element, it seems like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I also think, like, in part.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): what I wanted to do was, oh, part of…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): the initial germ also was wanting to do, like, a mystery box. It's like, I really like mystery box TV shows, where, like, little pieces of the larger mystery, you know, of what the world is are gradually revealed, like, episode by episode. Yeah.
Eric Rosenbaum: Mmm.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And so, like, that… I also think, like, that structure… for a mystery.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): means that, like, there were certain pieces of information and clues, like, it… there's a way that it's more on rails, because.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Well, there were lots of…
Eric Rosenbaum: to reveal.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The mystery story I wanted to tell was progressive, which I think is, like, a different in kind sort of a game than…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You know, dragging that.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, I don't think any of us mind playing in…
Tim Sackton: tightly scripted games, it's… it's sort of… it's slightly… like, you wouldn't want to put this on Reddit. You get a million people who say you're a terrible DM because players have no agency, but I don't think…
Tim Sackton: We feel that way, so…
Mike Sackton: I actually…
Eric Rosenbaum: Excellent illusion of agency.
Mike Sackton: But I actually felt like there was a lot of… choices.
Mike Sackton: Yeah. Right? I actually felt the narrative…
Tim Sackton: There was one… there was one big choice.
Mike Sackton: There was one big choice.
Mike Sackton: And there was a fair number of, I think.
Mike Sackton: It felt like it was very narratively structured, such that there wasn't a lot
Mike Sackton: plot or game-wise happening sometimes, in the sense that it wasn't like we had a…
Mike Sackton: There wasn't a lot of, like.
Mike Sackton: of the more gamified aspects of D&D, right? Like, there wasn't a… a…
Eric Rosenbaum: I remember one combat where there…
Mike Sackton: There was one combat, no, there's only one.
Tim Sackton: Yeah.
Mike Sackton: It was a single combat, and even in the scenarios where.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): For fairness, though, I offered you a combat with Monistheus, and you declined.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, but mostly players don't want… like, nobody really wants… no character, even if… I mean, I might have enjoyed that combat, because I like combat, but, like, Char definitely doesn't want to fight.
Tim Sackton: If you can't avoid it, right?
Tim Sackton: Unless you can avoid it.
Mike Sackton: But…
Eric Rosenbaum: Schwartz.
Mike Sackton: Go, go ahead.
Eric Rosenbaum: Schwartz, have you read, the Hyperion novels?
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh. Oh, they're amazing? I think you would like them.
Eric Rosenbaum: there is an image in there that, to me, felt very much like it might have been an inspiration for your entity, but I guess not.
Eric Rosenbaum: It's called the Tree of Pain.
Tim Sackton: Hmm.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): How interesting. No.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I got… I really… early on in the process, I was really into this idea of, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Windblown seeds and, like, the alien-ness of a… of a something just casting its little bits out.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Schwartz.
David S. Kong: Schwartz, I'm, like, I'm, like, so, like, this, this whole, like, this, this, the, the vignette that you created was so fucking rich.
David S. Kong: And so fucking deep, and detailed, and so, like… it was… it was just, like, many, many, many, many layers of, like, deep thoughtfulness, which was… it was so, like, gloriously constructed.
David S. Kong: And the mood, and, like, you know, just, like, all the monologues were so fucking sick. I mean, they're… it was a real, like, they're very hypnotic.
David S. Kong: Also, just, like, I, like, again, just, like, fucking around with the music. There were some times where you were talking, like, you were doing a monologue, and then the music would just, you know, it was, like, fairly random in terms of, like, the various playlists and stuff that I was fucking with, but it would, like, lie, and I was like, oh, shit, it felt, like, super, like, cinematic, you know what I mean? It was just, like, it was, like…
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
David S. Kong: It was really, like, fucking sick.
David S. Kong: My one, like, so, okay.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, man, can I say that? I started off,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I had, like, a playlist I was listening over and over, and I started calling each of the session titles by the songs that I was thinking about for writing that session, and then gave up on that at some point. I should send that to you, Tim, for updating the…
Tim Sackton: Yeah, I can replace the session titles. I… there was a few… there are a few early ones had…
Tim Sackton: what, Mr. Blue Sky or something like that?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, yeah.
Tim Sackton: I forget what it was.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): There's a Russian song that I wish I had thought to play at the.
Tim Sackton: Dark as the night.
David S. Kong: Oh, you were gonna play one for the credits, you said.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, I was. I… Yeah.
David S. Kong: Played at the very…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'll send it out, I'll send it out.
David S. Kong: But my… well, the one thing I was gonna say is, like.
David S. Kong: Like, when you were just sharing, like, all of the different, like, possibilities of, like, what could have happened, or, like, the things we could, like…
David S. Kong: for, like, as a player, like, I… it was, like.
David S. Kong: I, like, part of what I wish is that I had, as a character.
David S. Kong: been able to either grok or, like, know how deep it could have gone. Do you know what I mean?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, yeah.
David S. Kong: Like, like, it was, it was…
Eric Rosenbaum: Such a, like.
David S. Kong: like, I feel like, it was so fucking, like… like, part of what I love just about any kind of creative, or, like, any, like, artist, anything, it's like, it's just, like, not stopping at the second thing, it's, like, going deeper and deeper, and then you're just like, oh, fuck, and then just, like, following all those threads all the way down.
David S. Kong: And this world actually had that. Like, it actually, like, just even at the end, you were explaining all these different permutations and ways that we could have done all of these different things.
David S. Kong: And they… it just didn't… like… like, for me as, like, my character, and even for me, like, as Dave, like, I didn't know how deep the fucking well went, you know what I mean?
Mike Sackton: It's D.
David S. Kong: Yeah, and so one thing is, like, how… I don't know how, just because, like, it was such a rich, like, web of possibilities, but, like, there were some.
Mike Sackton: Everything. Everything got to be 10 times more obvious.
David S. Kong: What's that?
Mike Sackton: Like, everything has to be 10 times… like, I agree with that. I did not really… partly it's because, like, we've been playing… a lot of the plot… a lot of the detail drops are coming late at night, and not all of us are necessarily always as awake, but…
Mike Sackton: Part of it is also just, it's hard to follow everything that's happening, and so…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I…
Eric Rosenbaum: campaigns.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I think part of the reason Tim was the one who was talking through the whole thing
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Was, like, in such a… it's almost like a text-heavy game, this one.
David S. Kong: Hmm.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): he was the one who got to spend the most time with the text afterwards, so the stuff that pops out in text doesn't.
David S. Kong: Sweet.
Mike Sackton: I found.
Tim Sackton: Right?
Tim Sackton: Sorry, go ahead, Mike.
Mike Sackton: I was gonna say, I found that the… That the mystery box…
Mike Sackton: depth of imagination in the actual plot was harder to respond to, because I often wasn't totally sure
Mike Sackton: exactly what was going on, or I didn't have all the pieces, but I found the narrative richness actually made me much more into playing my character, so I've very heavily leaned into the… look, Edric's intelligence is only 9. He has no idea what's going on, so let's just
Mike Sackton: Well, it's just, like, I actually had a huge amount of fun just playing up the kind of…
David S. Kong: Eatric was the moral center, otherwise we wouldn't have known what the fuck to do, because it was just like, well, like, there's endless things to do, and, like, it was just very… okay, alright, cool.
Mike Sackton: There was something about the…
Mike Sackton: I mean, I was thinking when you're saying you, like, had these core monologues, there's something about the way that all fit together that made it…
Mike Sackton: A lot easier to… Focus more on…
Mike Sackton: like, character's experience, whereas, like, say…
David S. Kong: Kim's good.
Mike Sackton: games, I'm often… focused on… the…
Mike Sackton: Richness of the plot in a way that takes away a little bit from focusing on your character.
Tim Sackton: So…
Mike Sackton: Which isn't bad, it's… it's… Right.
Tim Sackton: Right, right. I noticed this, too. I mean, I have a different experience with these games, always, because…
Tim Sackton: Part of what makes it easy to figure out is if you've written 80% of Taldarverse.
Tim Sackton: like, you see the connections that, like, I… there's no way that, like, totally would be… I would be shocked if any of you caught the far realm deep cut.
Tim Sackton: Draw.
Mike Sackton: The thing is, I literally looked up that book when Schwartz mentioned it, but I did not put 2&D together as…
Tim Sackton: Rev.
Mike Sackton: Bart ride.
Tim Sackton: But it's different… having written something and just looking something.
Mike Sackton: No.
Tim Sackton: is a very different experience, right? And I spent a huge amount of time constructing the whole intellectual history of.
Kate Sackton: Something could come from the far realms and be totally bad, or something could come from the far realms and be totally good, or something could come from the far realms and be ambiguous. Yeah. Like, really hope that it was from the Far Realms.
Tim Sackton: No, no, no, the point was that there was a book… there was a specific book that was missing from the library.
Kate Sackton: Yeah.
Tim Sackton: And the book was a book about the Far Realms, that was specifically one of the books that was…
Tim Sackton: arguing the Far Realms is not, but it was the Far Realms connection that seemed super obvious to me from that book.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, I mean, talk about writing, like, there were moments in prep for some of the sessions where I felt like, is this too obvious? And the answer is, no, not even.
Tim Sackton: No, it's never on too honest. But what I wanted to say is.
Tim Sackton: What I wanted to say is, I think there is a… The mystery box…
Tim Sackton: works great as long as the player… as long as you're being carried by the narrative, right? So as soon as it wasn't a puzzle about us trying to solve the Rubik's Cube, but it was a puzzle about.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yep.
Tim Sackton: just being carried along by the story and figuring it out. Because what causes… I think what…
Eric Rosenbaum: Hmm. What?
Tim Sackton: So, so the plots, like, this type of stuff that happens in… happened in Denver, where it's a plot that you're supposed to be able to figure out.
Tim Sackton: in some ways, I'm actually kind of trying to lean against that, because it encourages a lot of out-of-character, like, intellectualization of, like.
Eric Rosenbaum: Damn.
Tim Sackton: solving the puzzle, and you can't actually solve puzzles in character, right? Like, you solve puzzles out of character, and if they're puzzles that you can put together clues by talking about, you inevitably do that out of character. And I understand that's fun, and everybody likes that, and like…
Tim Sackton: But there's… there is something appealing about…
Tim Sackton: Actually, just not being able to solve the puzzle.
Tim Sackton: Like, that forces you to just be carried along by the narrative, and so you piece it together much more in character.
Tim Sackton: Because there wasn't any moment where it was obvious, like, we should have a two-hour discussion about what's going on, and try and piece it together, right?
David S. Kong: Well, Schwartz, I mean, that's kind of like… like, like, what… I think what y'all are saying, I totally agree with, it's like, how…
David S. Kong: I agree very much that, there was a lot of great, like, inner reflection about the character, and I also thought, like, that very ending where we all told, like, those, like… I thought everybody's story was fucking sick, by the way. I thought everybody did.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Glad I was…
David S. Kong: So…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm impressed, that was amazing.
David S. Kong: No, but Schwartz, I think you did a great job, like, giving us, like, it was, like, kind of a high.
Eric Rosenbaum: Right.
David S. Kong: Simple enough prompt, but then we could kind of all, like, go into art. So, I super agree with Michael that you're saying, it's like.
David S. Kong: like, even though there was this, like, deep realm of choices that we could have made to do all this fucking time junking and blah blah blah, like, in a way, like, like, Kato Min was just like, I don't know what the fuck is going on, I'm in a dark place, but I'm also, like… and it really was, I think, like, I felt me, like, Dave Kong playing this character, I was embracing… I just felt the same, like, totally lost as, like, my character felt, and then it was just sort of like, okay, cool, like.
David S. Kong: So there was a certain element of, like, getting swept away into the… and because the narrative was so rich and the vibe was so, like, thick, you know?
David S. Kong: And Schwartz, the other thing, too, is, like, I remember from the very first one, it was, like, it just felt like a Kubrick movie, you know what I mean?
David S. Kong: like, I think, remarkably, every session still felt like that. Like, every… even though it kind of.
Eric Rosenbaum: shifted to…
David S. Kong: like, different scenes or whatever, like… like, it felt like every… it was a… it was just a very, like, moody, like, rich, yeah, narratively rich, and then, like, you know, how your narrative, like, kind of hooked it all in.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That makes me so happy.
David S. Kong: Oh, dude, it was… it was a vibe. It was a fucking vibe, and it was just like… but it was… but it was also did feel like, I don't know what's going on, like, I don't know, like, it's like, clearly there's all this, like, shit happening, and there's, like, a lot of complexity in here. I… I, Dave Kong, don't understand it. My character doesn't understand it, but I'm having a great time, like, experiencing it all, and it's almost like now, at the very end.
David S. Kong: Realizing all this other stuff. My only thing is, like, oh, like.
David S. Kong: could I… would it have been more fun to have known that I could have done some of that? Because, like, it was still awesome. It was still, like, 10 out of 10.
Tim Sackton: I actually think it was…
David S. Kong: matter, you know.
Kate Sackton: I need to say that this was utterly wonderful, but I cannot stay.
Tim Sackton: You're going today.
Kate Sackton: Yeah, yeah, awesome.
David S. Kong: Yeah.
Kate Sackton: Y'all, y'all can keep… as much as.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Have a good night.
Kate Sackton: Beautiful story.
Kate Sackton: merits, but yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Happy to bring up.
Kate Sackton: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Literally here.
Kate Sackton: Thank you for one.
Tim Sackton: Oh, yeah.
Kate Sackton: Get a word in edgewise and say goodnight!
Mike Sackton: Thank you.
David S. Kong: Hi, Kate, bye-bye.
Tim Sackton: Yay.
Tim Sackton: What I… and I'm sure Mike wants to go.
Mike Sackton: I offered a badge.
Tim Sackton: Schwartz, I need to, like, run down a few facts with you.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, that'd be really fun.
Tim Sackton: Oh.
Tim Sackton: So I can make your Tago bursting.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Can I respond to what Kong was just saying?
David S. Kong: Please, yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): She's like… Part of… part of what I had in mind was.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): what were the things that I could do to make it more of, like, a feeling game than a thinking game?
David S. Kong: Yeah.
Eric Rosenbaum: Mmm, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): part of what I was trying to do, like, with all… I think almost every session, the prompts at the beginning were, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): one way or another, like, what is your character feeling? Like, what are you scared of? What are you excited about?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): worried about? Like, that… that sort of supported, like, that angle.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And then the other piece of it, too, is, like,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): one of the other things really early on in the process for me was knowing that it was going to be this twilight state, like, this hour after a sunset feeling, and then to think, like, how to bring that through the whole experience. So, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I forget what it is exactly, but, like, in Hulda's story, so you are arriving at the house at sunset. You're meeting him right when the last rays of sun are finishing.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): in his story, he's talking, to some effect about, like, how he feels like the best, like, the peak has already passed him by, and now things are winding down. So, like, part of what I'm trying to do is, like, anticipate
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): the experience I know you're gonna be having in future sessions, and…
Eric Rosenbaum: Wow.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And the same, too, like, in some of what the Erythrama Slamperin people were saying, and I don't know, just to try and… Yeah. …keep that motif going.
David S. Kong: But I guess what I'm trying to get, again, you know, for me, as I'm now, like, you know, preparing for, you know, to DM this, like, next bit, it's like.
David S. Kong: like… from a player perspective, and, like, a me, Dave Kong perspective.
David S. Kong: I thought about… I was like, it was massively satisfying, even though, like, neither myself or my character totally understood the various other choices that were possible. Do you know what I mean? So in that way, it was, like, it was a huge success, and, like, etc. But I'm, like, kind of wondering, for myself, like, in, like, running a game, it's like, well.
David S. Kong: Is it… is it actually…
David S. Kong: Like, how much of the satisfaction, like, kind of connects into, like, feeling like your characters have, like, choice
David S. Kong: to do different… well, but actually, you know, but even like you're describing, right? It's like, if we had chosen, like, instead of the child, it actually would have been a totally different experience. So we did have, like, agency. We actually had quite a lot of agency, like, at certain levels, but…
Mike Sackton: You know what I'm saying?
David S. Kong: It's sort of like this tension between.
Mike Sackton: I think you need…
David S. Kong: You know?
Mike Sackton: you need agency on some dimension, whether it's thought, or whether it's narrative, or… I mean, I felt like there was a lot of agency in
Mike Sackton: Schwartz really set it up so that there was a strong
Mike Sackton: So, I mean, I think it was very strong feel… for me at least, it was a very strong feeling type experience, and so it felt like there was a lot of moments where what your character was feeling, or how your character was reacting to the moment, seemed like it would matter.
Mike Sackton: Whether it really did or not actually didn't matter, but it seemed like it would matter, and so it gave a lot of points of choice about
Mike Sackton: how are you reacting to this experience that wasn't necessarily… A plot base, they're like.
Tim Sackton: But also, I mean, there was a big choice at the end.
Mike Sackton: Yes, yes.
Tim Sackton: came very close to taking the key and going back to…
Mike Sackton: React.
Tim Sackton: Lord Endlessly ending, and it was clear that that was a possibility, so it wasn't… it wasn't a…
Tim Sackton: there wasn't no agency in the sense that we could've… that, like, we were gonna end up in the room no matter what we did. And we could've…
Tim Sackton: pushed harder to just… I mean, Charo maybe would have pushed harder to… To go down the tunnel.
Tim Sackton: and come out in 1351 if Egypt wasn't so committed to the moral cause of, like, Boom.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I was kicking myself a little bit, too, for having Moniclius not come into the room with you, because if he was in there.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): He could… he could have been a way to invite the time
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): He could have been a way to plant the idea that you can go to any time you want, right?
David S. Kong: Yeah. Yeah.
Eric Rosenbaum: 11.
Tim Sackton: But I think…
Mike Sackton: I didn't need that choice, honestly.
Tim Sackton: Is my point. But it's not… I think my… my… what I'm trying to get to for…
Tim Sackton: for Kong is that…
Tim Sackton: there's lots of… I think there's a lot of ways to do it right, and there's a lot of ways that are satisfying.
Tim Sackton: And… I wouldn't… I don't think it's a situation where
Tim Sackton: I actually think it's better to focus on one dimension than the other, right? I think if this plot had been a mystery that we could pick apart more clearly.
Tim Sackton: I… something, right?
Tim Sackton: Then, it actually might have worked less well, because…
Tim Sackton: Schwartz's style is much more in the kind of…
Tim Sackton: Story arc, and you can't have a mystery that the players are totally free to solve, and a strong narrative push.
Tim Sackton: that's carried by the DM, because those then end up in conflict, right? You have to pick one lane or the other.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You know, that's part of the difference between, like, a game that's a mystery and a mystery box, where in the mystery box.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It's fun and enjoyable to speculate about what's going on, but there isn't actually a way to solve it until the narrative presents you with all of the information. Right, right.
Mike Sackton: I don't…
Tim Sackton: There wasn't really a choice we could have made differently that would have allowed us to
Tim Sackton: understand who the prisoner… like, all the clues…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): No, no, wait a minute, wait a minute, wait a minute. There absolutely it is. You could have rolled a goddamn investigation check in every single room with a book that you walked into, and…
David S. Kong: And then we'll.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): No, no.
David S. Kong: What happened?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Me… this actually… this is not really a complaint. Me in the early sessions, I had prepped, like, half of the books that you ended up reading in the later sessions.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): were originally going to be available to you in Dandelion House. Like, there was a library there with books, and I just assumed that you all, being the players that you are, would not pass up that proffer.
Tim Sackton: You… you four, as players, have never once researched a question. If I didn't… if I did not provide, like.
Tim Sackton: Five strong clues that you have to research this question, or you will die.
Mike Sackton: I don't think the basic mechanic of rolling to find things out is actually that fun.
Tim Sackton: No, it's really not.
Eric Rosenbaum: That's the problem.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I would also have accepted what books are in the library.
Mike Sackton: That's fair, right? Like, I would just say, I need to go to bed, but I think you should just lean into your straights, like… Right. From a prepping perspective, it's like, don't…
Mike Sackton: Like, this worked really well as a narrative.
Mike Sackton: ARC.
Mike Sackton: Because Schwartz just leaned into the narrative arc and didn't really… It didn't matter that the…
Mike Sackton: like, trying to do everything in a mini-session is a terrible idea, right?
Tim Sackton: Damn.
Mike Sackton: Pick something to make it the focus of, and…
Eric Rosenbaum: And you're a strong improviser, Kong, and so as long as you have the kind of bones of the world and of the motivations of the characters that we're gonna.
Mike Sackton: I'm excited.
Eric Rosenbaum: I built it.
Mike Sackton: Like, full on…
Eric Rosenbaum: thought.
Mike Sackton: Deep box battles, and, you know…
David S. Kong: No, it's actually, like, I'm actually, I've got the arc, like, figured out of, like, overall, like, kind of what the story is, but I think what I'm… what I'm feeling through, and, you know, again, it's like, like.
David S. Kong: I think what y'all are saying is so true. It's like, just as a DM, like, you just gotta be you, and you gotta kinda do the things that feel, like, right and true to you, which I think is totally right.
David S. Kong: The, the kind of logistical, mechanical things that I'm feeling through are those, like, elements of, like, yeah, like, like, Schwartz, like, I thought, like, just little things that you did, I thought were really, really, like, just really just neat, like.
David S. Kong: you know, even… but very cinematic, you know what I mean? Like, even at the end, like, bringing us back to every single character that you introduced, and kind of showing, like, what happened in that. Like, it was just, like, there were a lot of very satisfying, like, like, kind of things like that, that were just, like, really,
David S. Kong: like, I guess what I'm trying to say is, like, every single moment, like, in a campaign, as a player, there are just these satisfying moments where you're like, fuck yeah, this is why D&D is awesome, you know what I mean? It's sort of like, you know, we've talked about this, it's like, one of my all-time favorites was
David S. Kong: You know, when we were, the storm giant, and, like, realizing, like, you know.
Mike Sackton: Yeah, yeah.
David S. Kong: Sky was just like, wow, this is so satisfying, you know? It's just like, it's like, like, and it's sort of like, from a DM perspective, and from a design perspective, it's like, how do you design each session so that there's at least, like, kind of one really satisfying moment for the players to kind of either reveal something, or discover something, or, like, there's some kind of play, you know what I mean? Where it's like, you just get that, you know? So, like, that's sort of what I'm… I'm not, like, overthinking it, but it's sort of, like, being inspired by, like.
David S. Kong: like, the various things that I've experienced with you all as DAs.
Tim Sackton: Yeah.
David S. Kong: And then being like, oh, like, what are those elements that, like.
David S. Kong: Just, just from a design perspective, to make sure that, like, each session's gonna have at least, like, one kind of, like, satisfying moment, you know?
Eric Rosenbaum: It's really hard to do the rug pull thing…
Eric Rosenbaum: I think that Schwartz does. It takes a lot of orchestrating.
Eric Rosenbaum: Oh.
Eric Rosenbaum: Am I frozen?
Mike Sackton: Nope.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, you're there. We can hear you.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, yeah.
Eric Rosenbaum: I was just gonna say, like…
Eric Rosenbaum: To carefully set up an expectation, and then violate it so that we're surprised, or the sense of wonder.
Eric Rosenbaum: I think that's… I'm on mute.
Eric Rosenbaum: a bit in tension with, like, the player creativity thing that I'm after, so I'm thinking about, like, how to make a world that's more of a sandbox than a story.
Mike Sackton: Yeah.
Mike Sackton: Until we actually…
Eric Rosenbaum: I just don't even… I don't know what's gonna happen.
Mike Sackton: the…
Mike Sackton: I'm not even sure how much I experienced the lug pull. I mean, to me, it felt more like it was sort of…
Mike Sackton: unclear.
Mike Sackton: I was never confident enough about anything in particular to feel a particular… Yeah.
Tim Sackton: I didn't see it as a rug pull, I thought it… I saw it much more as a… it's never clear what the…
Tim Sackton: it was never clear what… other than wanting to go home, which was Char's primary motivation, it was never clear what the… where he would come down, because it was genuinely uncertain, like…
Mike Sackton: Goodbye.
David S. Kong: Well, the other part of it is, I feel like, as players, we really were pawns in, like, a way bigger fucking thing.
David S. Kong: So much bigger and beyond any of us.
David S. Kong: You know, it's sort of like, you know, like, like, in the kind of canonical, like, Talgar with, like, you know, in the Tim campaigns, it's like, we're the heroes, and, like, there's, like, kind of all of this, like, ways in which we're these, like, kind of central characters, and this one was just, like, we're not, like, like, yeah, like, we did a thing that ended up being important, but it was sort of like, it was, it was like, like, there's just, it was just all of this shit that was so much not about us, like, at all. Like, we were just other souls walking down.
David S. Kong: road, almost, that kind of, you know, got pulled in this thing, which was great. It was like, we're just, like, these other, you know, so there was a certain, like, lack of, like, like, feeling of powerlessness, almost, that was, like, kind of…
David S. Kong: Cool.
Eric Rosenbaum: I think that makes me think of Kong for the… for the drug in it.
Eric Rosenbaum: game is… If there could be a kind of mischief vibe, where…
Eric Rosenbaum: It's not that we're huge and powerful, but you just choose the right domino to knock over, and then it sets off a crazy cascade of events in subdirection.
Eric Rosenbaum: Right.
David S. Kong: Yeah, I mean, the Dragon Nut thing, I've got, like, a strong plot that I'm excited about that I think will be fun and will be satisfying, but I think, like, the, like, yeah, I'm just feeling through these little bits, man. It's just, like, it's a really… just, like, all these kind of different balances of, like, well, you know, like…
David S. Kong: like…
David S. Kong: Yeah, I don't know, it's just like, I don't even know how to, like, kind of analyze well what makes different sessions and moments, like, really satisfying.
Tim Sackton: Yeah.
David S. Kong: It's kind of, like, reflecting back for myself, like, oh, like, that was really fucking cool.
Tim Sackton: You kind of just have to do it and see what works for you, because it's gonna be different for everybody. It's also… the other thing to keep in mind is that
Tim Sackton: the world seems super different to a player than a DM. It's actually been super interesting.
Eric Rosenbaum: for me to…
Tim Sackton: actually play, and I think it's, like.
Tim Sackton: I'm getting all sorts of ideas for how to run games better, like the searching thing. Like, it's actually really hard to figure out how to communicate to players that there is information you should look for here.
Tim Sackton: Like, it's totally non-obvious.
Tim Sackton: You think you say library, and you think that communicates to a player.
Tim Sackton: oh, there's information in the library, but it absolutely does not. And…
Eric Rosenbaum: Like, that research mechanic is not fun, because it's a little bit like the teacher asking a question where they want you to read their mind or something. It's like…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, that's the…
Tim Sackton: No, that's what I mean, is that you can't just say, oh, there's a library, you should know to ask for it, right? There has to be some other way to…
Tim Sackton: spark curiosity. Like, that's what you need to do. You need to…
Tim Sackton: Spark some curiosity about what defined.
Eric Rosenbaum: you give a clue that's for free, and then they have to ask some kind of follow-up question to investigate further. It's not like, you should investigate here.
Mike Sackton: It's hard, though.
Eric Rosenbaum: A little bit of something.
Mike Sackton: I mean, it's very tricky, because you either need to have made up a ton of information, so you can present all of the puzzle pieces to the players as actual in-world puzzle pieces.
Mike Sackton: Or, it's very difficult to, like.
Mike Sackton: you don't want to just tell people the it. You're, like, it's, like, the problem with a library of books is what do you… what do you…
Mike Sackton: put it… put in the… when you say, if you read the book, right? Like, one option is you, like, literally have 10 pages from the book written down, and you're like, here's what you find, and you have to, like, discover… the players have to discover the clue within the 10 pages.
Mike Sackton: But if you're not gonna do that, you… if you're reduced to just, like, well, you roll, and if you roll well enough, I tell you the clue.
Tim Sackton: Right, that's boring.
Mike Sackton: That's kind of boring, right? Like, that's a crappy mechanic.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, I wonder a little bit, like, even…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): even having RA there saying, like, what can I help you find? Like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That sort of a prompt was, what is the… seems to invite, like, what is the specific book you're looking for? What is the specific question you have?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And it almost feels like
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): like, the better prompt in some kind would have been to ask instead, like, what open questions do you have? Or, like, what unresolved… like, what… what are the unknowns that you're wrestling with? And… and I'll help you find, like…
Tim Sackton: I think it's tricky because…
Tim Sackton: Because… so I'm actually thinking back to some of the times in Dunmar where you actually did, like, pursue research, and it was… and it was usually because you had come up with some idea.
Tim Sackton: And you were like, we want to figure this idea out, right? So you did a ton of stuff about, like, Ryze, the pieces of Rye's hand, and the elderwood, and, like, what are all the rumors, right? But it really…
Tim Sackton: It's really hard to get players to do research on
Tim Sackton: the mysteries that the DM creates, because…
Tim Sackton: You don't even know what you're supposed to research.
Mike Sackton: Rev.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah, they might be real. Schwartz…
David S. Kong: I actually thought our RA, like, interacting with the RA, was actually really satisfying.
Mike Sackton: Yeah.
David S. Kong: player, because even though it was sort of like… instead of it sort of being like, oh, like, let's do some research, and we send it out, and then we see… it was like this kind of live… it was like a live chat bot, right? But you kind of sit there and be like, what kind of weird questions can I ask? And then, you know, you're really good at just, like, kind of being, like, the right level of, like.
Tim Sackton: Yeah.
David S. Kong: Whatever, so it was still a very satisfying…
Mike Sackton: That was…
David S. Kong: But I think, and this also goes back strategically into the use of, like, NPCs, and, like, how do you have, like, along with the party, like, some entity or, you know, way for the party to, like, query something to, like, help it, like, you're fucking stuck doing a thing that, like, is dumb, or whatever, and then it's like, oh, look, like, actually, you know, let me help you out a little bit, and kind of, you know?
David S. Kong: That's.
Eric Rosenbaum: A DM sometimes needs a proxy in the world.
David S. Kong: Exactly, exactly, right, which… which… yeah, we menaced the C's, and then… and then the RA both kind of served that a little bit.
Mike Sackton: I mean, and this game worked, or a lot of these things worked well, because there was no…
Mike Sackton: our character…
Mike Sackton: a lot of the character sheet itself was very light. One of the other problems I feel like you run into with some of these things is, like, if you are a player who
Mike Sackton: if you are a character like Seeker, who invests a lot in skills, in Dunbar, Seeker was always like, well, let's roll Arcana, right? Like, you… you…
Mike Sackton: It's not that fun to be the player who's invested in a lot in being good at research, and then actually…
Mike Sackton: You're no better at research than anybody else.
David S. Kong: Right.
Mike Sackton: That's the mechanic that's always difficult with…
Tim Sackton: I mean, the thing that I try to do that I'm not… sorry, go ahead, Schwartz.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): just briefly, I also feel like I experienced the flip side of that a little bit, that, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Welby had all of these skills, and it seemed like… It didn't seem very fun…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): To just, like, roll a skill, to be like…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I'm gonna roll the die, and that's the thing, like, I… there was part of me that wanted to, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I don't know.
Mike Sackton: I… well, so I'll just throw it in my…
Mike Sackton: other game, one of the things I…
Mike Sackton: stumbled on, I didn't really plan it this way, but it actually worked really well, was that
Mike Sackton: there was… I made… the players were in the Feywild and were in… trying to find information.
Mike Sackton: Right? And I basically had to skill check determine how many questions they could ask.
Eric Rosenbaum: Hmm.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Oh, that's… that's an interesting way to do it. Which…
Mike Sackton: I mean, it was a specific context where they were… they were…
Mike Sackton: interacting with a group of people who was going to basically stop answering their questions after a period of time. And it actually worked really well, to be like, oh.
Mike Sackton: you roll poor, you only get two questions, right? Versus you roll loud, you get seven questions, right? Like, it doesn't work in every context, but it could actually work in a library situation as well. You just have to suspend disbelief that
Mike Sackton: you can… you have to just sort of all accept as a group of players that you rolled badly. It means the universe conspired to make it unsuccessful for you to learn more information, even if you keep trying for many, many, many, many extra hours, right?
Mike Sackton: Otherwise, it's like, well, why don't I only get two questions? What if I try again tomorrow? Can I get two more questions?
Mike Sackton: Yep. Doubt.
Tim Sackton: Correct. Yeah.
Mike Sackton: I have to go to bed.
Tim Sackton: You may ask my bank, and this is…
Mike Sackton: I'm gonna… Go ahead.
David S. Kong: really ask, because I just, this is like a Dragon X thing.
Mike Sackton: Right?
David S. Kong: Before you guys, I'll leave. So… That, like.
David S. Kong: my hope for the Dragonettes is that, again, just as it relates to, like, mechanics and, like, skill stuff, it's like the whole, like, like, going back, and Mike, I think you've said this, and it just, like, like, it just felt like a very strong thing, where it's like, you know, the cool thing about your character is, like, the little, like, you know, things that you've created that.
Mike Sackton: Yeah.
David S. Kong: like, and you, like, what's satisfying as a player is to get to do the things that your character… that you, like, the character, have created for yourself to go and do, right? So it's like, what I want to try to do…
David S. Kong: to scratch that satisfaction itch, again, is to sort of, like, in this… the next session when we all do our things, to, like, really kind of be creative about, like, what are the fun, random things as, like, you know, this is your first and maybe only time ever to play a Dragon Ant, so, like, this is, like, let's.
Mike Sackton: Yeah, yeah.
David S. Kong: You know? But I guess, like, I don't know if you guys have other, like, thoughts about how to scratch that itch better. Like, like, Schwartz, that's what you're kind of getting at. You're like, oh, like, I'm really skilled at all this stuff, but then there's something else you wanted
David S. Kong: Do you know what I mean? So, like, is there a way to just make that mechanic stronger?
David S. Kong: I mean… Yeah, go ahead, Mike.
Mike Sackton: I think a lot of what we're saying is actually that in D&D, the generalized skill mechanic kind of sucks.
Mike Sackton: Right? The problem is that BAD doesn't have a very good mechanic for skills in particular, because it doesn't have a good mechanic for things that should be
Mike Sackton: more granular than a Boolean success or failure. Skills are great if it's like, I'm trying to jump across a bridge, and I need to throw out acrobatics, but…
Mike Sackton: persuasion.
Mike Sackton: diploma, you know, why… like, there's lots of skills that… that are… are not a good binary, but I wouldn't try to solve that. Your magic thing about giving everybody little
Mike Sackton: with holes.
David S. Kong: Sparks, or whatever.
Mike Sackton: barks.
Mike Sackton: I would say, for Dragon Act, it's like, you almost de-emphasize, like, skills can't be the important thing about.
David S. Kong: No, I want it to be the custom thing that you think is cool about the Dragon Net that you… but… Go, Derek.
Eric Rosenbaum: So an idea for how it plays out. Schwartz is like, I'm gonna do something, not just roll the dice.
David S. Kong: Yeah.
Eric Rosenbaum: And so, we could generalize the storytelling mechanic, like we used in the final encounter tonight.
Eric Rosenbaum: to where… You want to use your skill. Well, how well?
Eric Rosenbaum: Does it work out? It depends how well you…
Eric Rosenbaum: Describe the idea of what your character.
Tim Sackton: Yeah.
Eric Rosenbaum: do.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It's a…
Eric Rosenbaum: And that's…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yep.
Eric Rosenbaum: Tim often has us do that, I think. Yeah.
Tim Sackton: I will say one thing. I think the main problem with D&D skills is that we as a group roll them way too infrequently.
Tim Sackton: Skills work much better if it's not… and I'm guilty of this, and I'm… my goal in the next campaign is to do better at this. Tending to be like a, okay, you're spending 20 minutes on this conversation, and then you get one persuasion check, and that's… then you're done.
Tim Sackton: Right? It's, like, not a really fun way to use skills, but if skills are more… if skills actually steer the… somehow steer the encounter.
Tim Sackton: Right? Then…
Tim Sackton: The outcome of each role matters a little bit, and it changes things, but there's not, like, one…
Mike Sackton: you want to avoid the skill being a success. Skills don't work well as success or failures for anything that matters, is, I think, another way of putting it, right? You want it to be, like.
Mike Sackton: You said two things, and you make a persuasion check, and that tells you how well they respond to it, but that doesn't necessarily mean you get what you want.
David S. Kong: Right, right. Well, I guess, like, like, Schwartz, one of the things that I thought was kind of, like, going back to this whole thing about, like, all the skills work, like, at the end of the day, it felt like the most important thing for our characters in your campaign was actually, like, related to this, like, the characters' stories and backstories and their own.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
David S. Kong: you know, it was not at all about skills, or like, you know, like, what you were good at, or what weapons you had. Like, none of that was really important at all. It was like… and that was actually really, I thought, really strong. It was, like, E-Jerk had this big moral thing, that drove the plot, Plato was going through this, like, existential crisis, and then, you know, like…
David S. Kong: It was… it was a completely, like, story-driven, character-driven.
David S. Kong: plot, and not at all about, really, skills or dicebreaking.
Mike Sackton: I will say the…
David S. Kong: Cool, like, it was really worked.
Mike Sackton: The mechanic in this session kind of sucked. I mean, it… It was fun, because…
Mike Sackton: it… of the way it worked out, but the actual mechanic, if you think about it, with a target number on a D20 over 5 people, actually sucks, because the variability is way, way, way too high compared to your pluses, right? So there's no… like, if you're like, oh, you're gonna get… you have to get 50 to win.
Mike Sackton: It's like, with only one role, it's actually very, very, very difficult to… Have that mechanic.
Mike Sackton: work well, and the problem with… it's the same trap Tim falls into. It's the same situation that we had in Dunmark, where it's fun, because you have an opportunity to tell a cool story and listen to everybody else's cool stories, and it's very enjoyable from a, like, human interaction
Mike Sackton: Role-playing narrative standpoint.
Mike Sackton: Right? But actually, from a gameplay standpoint, it's like…
Mike Sackton: Rolling one die across a bunch of people and having a buoyant success or failure is not actually a good game.
Mike Sackton: But it's a second game, even though it's a fun narrative.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): This is true.
Eric Rosenbaum: If you want.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Also.
Eric Rosenbaum: More, like, iteration, more continuity.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): You know, a target number for that?
Mike Sackton: No, of course not.
Tim Sackton: But it was…
Eric Rosenbaum: Crazy, didn't.
David S. Kong: There's no scenario where we weren't gonna get it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): the exchange.
Tim Sackton: Yeah.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I felt like if the… if the invitation was just, hey, tell a story, that's nice, and then you win, like, that… that doesn't… Yeah. Even though that is fun.
Tim Sackton: What it is, so don't sugarcoat it, just… just…
Tim Sackton: I don't think it's that satisfying to…
Tim Sackton: I mean, this was Mike's point about the… in Dunbar, when you were getting… when you were getting through the…
Tim Sackton: Monks, and everybody was, like, doing their…
Tim Sackton: Things is, like, don't make it a check if you're not gonna let it fail.
Tim Sackton: And you're not gonna let it fail, because, like, it wouldn't be totally unsatisfying for it to fail. So, like, what is… what is the die roll accomplishing there?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah. That's a good question.
Mike Sackton: I mean, I think there's ways, I don't know what the mechanic is, there probably are ways to make the die roll
Mike Sackton: actually accomplish something. I just… it… because it was actually fun to use rage and to have a sort of.
David S. Kong: That was cool. That was really cool.
Mike Sackton: I have an incentive to make the story fit with my character, right? Exactly.
David S. Kong: That was great. Yeah, Mike, that was really fucking cool when you did that.
Mike Sackton: So, like, if you're not rolling at all, it's like, you kind of take… But…
Mike Sackton: I mean, I think we all kind of knew there wasn't a…
Mike Sackton: there's a little bit of suspension this week, we know that there's not…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The key thing… the key thing that that mechanic accomplished
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): was helping the DM feel more like he was running a D&D game, and was using the rules and the dice and things.
Eric Rosenbaum: That's…
Mike Sackton: I do think there is…
Mike Sackton: and I haven't hit on it yet, but I do think there is a mechanic that would be… it's an interesting space to experiment, because we all like this kind of narrative skill.
Mike Sackton: In both, in a lot of games, it's fun to have this idea of a narrative skill interaction.
Mike Sackton: But it's always very unclear how to make dive rolling part of it meaningful.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I… I would love it to… Go, go ahead, sorry.
Eric Rosenbaum: We were just joking about the entity being bloodied.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah. You could actually… And make that several levels of detail, of description of, like, what the… Consequences are.
Mike Sackton: Well, I think combat works because it's very iterative, and you make many rolls, and so… no combat earlier.
Mike Sackton: Right? So, combat doesn't swing at a single roll. It's not like… it's not like you're resolving the combat with one D20 roll, and you either kill the monster or die.
Mike Sackton: Right.
Mike Sackton: And so, you can respond. There's options. There's, oh man, we're not convincing them, let's change tax. There's… so…
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
Mike Sackton: a… a… Right.
Mike Sackton: But combat also takes an hour.
Tim Sackton: So the one time I did this, that I'm not sure if Kong picked up on.
Tim Sackton: was in the Kenzo solo, and it was, like, there was this… there was, like, the chains of…
David S. Kong: Yes.
Tim Sackton: of,
David S. Kong: Yes, I remember that, yeah.
Tim Sackton: And there was one…
Tim Sackton: person you were trying to free, who you had… who's… who's, like… I forget what their fear was, but you had convinced yourself that what they wanted was the totally opposite of what they actually wanted. Yeah. And…
Tim Sackton: And the problem I ran into was it… the role kept failing.
Tim Sackton: But there was no way to, like, recover, right? There was no way to, like, figure out what you were doing wrong. And I think eventually you just did something generic, and I was like, okay, that's fine.
David S. Kong: Hmm.
Tim Sackton: Combat is obvious, like, you can tell, you take damage.
Tim Sackton: And I don't think D&D works… I don't think it makes sense to have a…
Tim Sackton: combat mechanic for this sort of thing, for these narrative things. But there needs to be…
Tim Sackton: And we try and do it, and I know, I mean, I try and do it, and Schwartz was doing it, right, where the thing responds to what you say.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
Tim Sackton: But I think… I think…
Tim Sackton: I think the way to make it a little bit more iterative and satisfying is a mechanic that actually feels
Tim Sackton: A little bit more like there's a real chance of failure, or at least a real chance of consequences, where
Tim Sackton: You know, you need to… reset and do something different is to actually…
Tim Sackton: It's tricky, because you don't want to have, like.
Tim Sackton: everybody doesn't want to tell 10 stories, right? It just takes too much time. But have some way that the…
Tim Sackton: you know.
Tim Sackton: as you start talking, maybe once it's sort of clear what the story is about, there's some way you can make a rule to see how it's responding. And one of the pieces of advice I've read is the way to think about these rules is not
Tim Sackton: you don't have an opinion about what the NPC thinks in advance. You roll a die, and that tells you what the NPC thinks, right? And so then you can have it be where there are some, like.
Tim Sackton: In this scenario, it was like, all of the stories were… Equally appealing to the entity.
Tim Sackton: That doesn't have to be the case, and there's a way that you can have the die roll
Tim Sackton: Have a… have multiple dive roles during the course of one story. That gives you a chance to actually have an early failure that you can still recover from, because your story doesn't resonate.
Tim Sackton: Right? Or something along those lines, right?
Eric Rosenbaum: I feel like the Hall of Stories was a little bit like that, because we didn't know how it worked at first, so we had to kind of figure it out and try different things.
Tim Sackton: Well, the… the… but… so, the thing about the Harlem story is, was…
Tim Sackton: the stakes of any one role were way lower, because what you were trying to do was, like, navigate through the stories to learn information. And so if you… when you failed, it was fine, like…
Tim Sackton: The… the fundamental problem is… is…
Tim Sackton: Failure being too unsatisfying to be a real option.
Tim Sackton: that kind of… Creates lots of mechanical problems, right?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I wonder a little bit about, like, What… what would it…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): It seems to me that often.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The die roll determines success or failure, and then, like, that's the…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): end of the thing. This is another variety of some of what you were just saying.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): But, like, I would…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I wonder how it would flow if the die roll goes, and then the DM asks the player, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): That's a success. How do you succeed?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): What… what did you say that convinced them? Why did you.
Eric Rosenbaum: I want to do it the opposite way. They're not respectful.
Tim Sackton: Oh, so…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): player is participating, and why… What the…
Tim Sackton: I don't… Go ahead, Mike.
Mike Sackton: I was just gonna say, that can be fun, but it doesn't change, like, in this particular scenario. It wouldn't…
Mike Sackton: Like, there needed to be… To make the die roll meaningful.
Mike Sackton: It would have had to have been the case that there was a recovery mechanism, right?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): about this scenario, yeah.
Mike Sackton: Right. I think the…
Tim Sackton: I don't…
Mike Sackton: beat.
Tim Sackton: I don't love that in general, because I feel like it's better for the die to reflect
Tim Sackton: How the world reacts to what you do, and not…
Tim Sackton: like, thinking about, like, you don't want to be a bard who rolls low and then has to be like, oh, I told a bad story, right? And you also can't control the NPC, so you don't want to be a bard who says, I told a great story, and they didn't like it for some reason.
Mike Sackton: Whoa.
Tim Sackton: waking up, right?
Mike Sackton: I actually disagree with that. I feel like…
Mike Sackton: if I was, like, thinking about dealt with in high persuasion.
Mike Sackton: I would have actually probably had a fair bit of fun with, like, you being like, why aren't you persuasive? I could be like, well, you know, the shadow armor just was too much.
Mike Sackton: Right? And it, you know… Right.
Eric Rosenbaum: Right.
Mike Sackton: There's actually… it gives you a… opportunity to…
Mike Sackton: Controlled and to, to sort of,
Eric Rosenbaum: I feel like I did that a lot with Seeker, like, different interesting ways that he messed things up.
Mike Sackton: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Tim Sackton: Right.
Mike Sackton: He took that out sometime in Europe, right?
Tim Sackton: I think it's… Yes, I think…
Tim Sackton: I'm not saying it's never good, I'm just saying I think that Generally speaking, it's useful for…
Tim Sackton: If you think of a die roll as reflecting how the world reacts to what the player said, it allows
Tim Sackton: the DM to, like, improvise more richly about NPCs, because…
Tim Sackton: Like, maybe there's an NPC, like, I don't know.
Tim Sackton: Early Kenz, though, didn't like elves, right? Like, you know, or didn't like shadow elves.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): early.
David S. Kong: Curly.
Tim Sackton: Nobody can stop it.
David S. Kong: I'll FaceTime Continuum capability.
Tim Sackton: Right? So… so maybe there's an NPC that just doesn't like Al, right?
Mike Sackton: But I don't necessarily think that… I mean, to your point that you like it when other people make things up, it's… there's a real possibility that that is…
Mike Sackton: Something that can be collaboratively decided. Does it always have to be up to the…
Tim Sackton: Yeah, yeah, no, no, no, I'm not… no, I'm not disagreeing at all, I'm just saying that I don't think it's an all-one, all the other situation, and…
Mike Sackton: to me, the challenges are both… and I really feel bad, but…
David S. Kong: Yeah.
Mike Sackton: I'm gonna leave you with two thoughts, and then I'm gonna go to bed.
Mike Sackton: I think the challenge is that when… Stakes are meaningful.
Mike Sackton: one and done is never satisfying, unless it's gonna be an automatic success, because otherwise it's too random, right? There's too much randomness in a single D20 roll.
David S. Kong: Yeah, right. Yeah, yeah.
Mike Sackton: And the other bit is that it feels kind of unsatisfying to…
Mike Sackton: there's not enough reflection of skill in… the D20 role is so variable compared to stats and pluses.
Mike Sackton: That you get into this scenario where
Mike Sackton: being the person who is good at persuasion doesn't really matter that much. On many… in combat, it's not like that, because you make many, many rolls. So on average, it comes out. But if you're only making.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah.
Mike Sackton: when making a small number of rolls, the D20 variability is so high compared to your pluses that you don't feel like.
Eric Rosenbaum: Interesting.
Mike Sackton: better, right? And so…
Tim Sackton: This is… this is my whole point. We should be making 5 times as many skill rolls a session. I think it would be more fun.
Mike Sackton: Yeah, or whatever it is, or whether it's… the failure is different depending on how good you are, or what… there's other options than just… but it's more satisfying to…
Mike Sackton: like, that was one thing that sort of annoyed me about Delaware, was, like.
Mike Sackton: Even with a plus 15 on persuasion.
Mike Sackton: Right? You roll… well, by the time you got to plus 15, this wasn't really a problem, but at lower levels, when…
Mike Sackton: he was still supposed to be the best at this. We didn't roll often enough that he actually was the best at it, and so it's a little bit… that becomes a little bit unsatisfying, right?
David S. Kong: Yeah, yeah.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah, that's true.
David S. Kong: That goes back to the, just, like, the design, like, the DM creating a situation where your characters just get to do the things that they're supposed to be good at, and, like, are fun for the player, you know, it's like, that's, like, you know…
David S. Kong: Right.
Tim Sackton: That's hard to keep in mind. I mean, I tried to do that with Wellbe and Seeker, where I would just give you extra information, but it's a lot of work, right? And it's hard to keep track of that all, and…
Tim Sackton: like, sometimes you just forget, right? And then you don't want your…
Tim Sackton: satisfaction of the player to rely on, like, the DM remembering some third-order thing.
Mike Sackton: I was just thinking that's where redirecting the failure back to the player, with this… especially if you had this kind of general agreement or understanding within the party, that if you're…
Mike Sackton: The guy with a plus 5 charisma and proficiency and expertise in persuasion.
Mike Sackton: your failures are going to be different than the failures for the guy who has a minus-one charisma and no proof, right? Like… and I think everybody would sort of get along with just role-playing that, right? Like, it's just like…
Mike Sackton: you know.
Mike Sackton: why did Egypt somebody of something? Well, because he just, like, stood there and said something totally dumb and made a total hash of it, whereas…
Mike Sackton: deal with probably failed because they're, you know, some sort of prejudiced asshole who doesn't like elves, because, you know, because of speciesism and, you know, the kind of nonsense that is out there in the world that we happen.
Tim Sackton: Thank you.
Mike Sackton: exterior B.
Tim Sackton: I think if Mike's gonna go to bed.
Mike Sackton: I'm gonna go back.
Tim Sackton: through the list of NPCs and places.
Mike Sackton: Good night.
Tim Sackton: I see.
David S. Kong: It's never my…
Tim Sackton: But I think just rolling more would be worth trying, right?
Tim Sackton: You roll a lot, each one has a small effect.
Tim Sackton: Cumulatively, it works better, and you're just rolling more dice, which is fun.
David S. Kong: Can I, can I ask you guys before I sign off if you guys are still gonna do it? Because, like, like, again, and just in terms of prep stuff, like, and, you know, Eric, feel free to hang for this, you may find this, like, meta discussion, like, what do you, like, what the fuck do you actually prepare? Like, is it, like…
David S. Kong: You know what I mean? Like, I actually, like, I've just been writing a whole bunch of stuff, like, in… in, like, my notes, and I've got, like, some, you know, but, like, shorts, like, for the sessions that you've been doing, like, what do you actually have that you're looking at? Like, is it, like, you wrote, like, do you have, like…
David S. Kong: like, actual, like, parts that you know you're gonna read out loud, like, written, and then, like, what do you actually have ready? Like, actually?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Can I… can I share a screen real quick? I think you have to stop sharing sound.
David S. Kong: Oh, interesting.
Eric Rosenbaum: I want to go to sleep, but I wanna see this.
David S. Kong: I can't… how do I stop sharing?
Tim Sackton: I allowed multiple percenters to share, you should be okay.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): So, I started with us all in a spreadsheet, and then moved away from that pretty quick. So, Google Doc, the first tab is, like, the overall story, and I added on to this… oops…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): like… The idea was that each of these would be one session.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And what's the plot skeleton at, like, a really high level, and then what are, like, the tasks that would move you through the plot skeleton, and the possible outcomes that I could imagine at the start.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): And then the house got its own tab.
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah, because…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Each room needed a space.
David S. Kong: That's great.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Characters got their own.
David S. Kong: with me? Schwartz?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, for sure, for sure.
Tim Sackton: Once you clone the Taldographer's repo, you'll get a huge amount of DM notes. Not the Dunmar Frontier DM notes, but pretty much all my other DM notes.
David S. Kong: Wow, alright.
Tim Sackton: They're super unorganized.
David S. Kong: No, but this is helpful, like, what I was looking for is, like, Google Doc with tabs. You know what I mean? Like, that's helpful, yeah.
Tim Sackton: Though, here, I'm gonna share my screen now.
Tim Sackton: Okay, so here's, like, my… here, I can even go into Denmark.
Eric Rosenbaum: So this is Obsidian, yeah.
Tim Sackton: with obsidian, here's, like, here's, like, this is what I'm gonna organize for Yukong. Here's the circular island.
Tim Sackton: I tend to do it differently. I have, like.
Tim Sackton: You know, these basically notes that are just, like.
David S. Kong: But is that what you'd prepare before each session?
Tim Sackton: Yeah, so these are, like, scenes, basically. I tend to organize things, like…
David S. Kong: Yeah, okay, that's cool.
Tim Sackton: I'll have, like, an outline.
Tim Sackton: That's just, like, random brainstorming. And then I have, for each session, I have DM notes. It's like an outline of what's gonna happen. I usually write out my intro.
Tim Sackton: It's all just bullet points and then scenes.
Eric Rosenbaum: Right.
Tim Sackton: Some of it has more stuff, right?
Tim Sackton: like, here's… here's, like, what is this from? The merfolk.
Tim Sackton: this is the information that… this is what you need, right? You need…
Tim Sackton: where the kelp forests are, a way to transport, and a way to water breathe. And this is just, like, brainstorming where you get this.
Tim Sackton: But I had… at this point, I had sort of stopped doing a lot of prep, because…
Tim Sackton: Like, this is totally unpredictable what you're gonna do, right, once you're this high level.
Tim Sackton: So it's just, like, notes about little sillies, right? Cities, like… vibe… locations, like…
David S. Kong: Yeah.
Tim Sackton: Vibe stuff like that.
David S. Kong: No, that's quite true. The concept of scenes makes a lot of sense, because you're gonna.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, so…
David S. Kong: Like, 2 or 3 of those, you know, per session, and then, you know.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, for some of these…
Tim Sackton: for, like, some of the more recent stuff I've been doing, I have… I actually have this, like.
Tim Sackton: Oh, this… this isn't filled out. Like, a template that's, like.
Tim Sackton: Basically, writing in a… writing an adventure.
Tim Sackton: That has, like, a lot more details, and this is probably over-designed for some things, but it's basically a structured way to have
Tim Sackton: These kinds of scenes, where you can have a bunch of scenes in here.
Tim Sackton: I haven't decided if I actually really like that.
David S. Kong: What's, what's Obsidian?
Eric Rosenbaum: Yeah, it's good.
Tim Sackton: Obsidian is… Obsidian is a… is a… good night, Eric. Obsidian is a…
Tim Sackton: Note-taking app that stores a collection of Markdown notes.
Tim Sackton: And lets you… link the notes with WikiLinks.
Tim Sackton: So it's like a personal wiki.
Tim Sackton: Which is really amazing for D&D notes, because, like, This is all of Taldarburse.
Tim Sackton: And it's all, like, organized, and then it's all linked.
Tim Sackton: And I can… and you can click on one of these links, You go to the note.
Tim Sackton: Right? You can just go from notes, and then you have, like, front mat… this is all way more complicated than…
Tim Sackton: Oh, and that's… that's not secret, okay?
Tim Sackton: But it's just, like, a way to have… Organize the Markdown notes.
David S. Kong: Yeah, I mean, I think… I think for what I'm gonna try to do, just given this little mini… mini campaign, I think, like, a Google Doc is perfect. A Google Doc with some tabs?
Tim Sackton: Yeah.
David S. Kong: We'll seat me back.
Tim Sackton: I used to… I used to do everything in Google Docs.
David S. Kong: Yeah, that's not super popular.
Tim Sackton: It works, it works well up to a point.
David S. Kong: Definitely, like, the instructions on how to do the thing that we talked about, that would be, that'd be great, and then Schwartz, yeah, if you don't mind sending over that, that, that, a link to your.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, I shared it already, yeah.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, Schwartz.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Chima, I have to go to bed, what, what, right.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I still have to drive home as part of the problem.
Tim Sackton: Okay.
Tim Sackton: 2 minutes.
Tim Sackton: Dad?
Tim Sackton: Yep. Dad?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yep.
Tim Sackton: Presumably…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Mushroom Man.
Tim Sackton: Pandel and the Rakshasa are just… they remain question marks. We don't need to know what happened to them.
Tim Sackton: Calypsis is the fungal golem.
Tim Sackton: Right?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yes, and is somewhere in the multiverse restarting, according to her, the Erythramous lampurum.
Tim Sackton: What did you say Lord Endlessly Ending's name was now?
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yep, Lord of the Ended Rev.
Tim Sackton: Rebel, of course.
Tim Sackton: The dandelion house is destroyed.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yep.
Tim Sackton: Twilight Kingdom is Quiet Kingdom, Lord Endlessly Ending's Manor is still a manor, but not a party.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): No, it's… right, Lord of the Ended Rebels Manor, yeah, that's exactly right, yep.
Tim Sackton: The 27,000 destroyed.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): The promontory is still there, and the well outside the universe is still there.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, the well is still open.
Tim Sackton: And then…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Our AI would reclassify not as dead, but as inanimate. Like…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I don't know if that's a meaningful distinction.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, yeah, that's… that's meaningful.
Tim Sackton: I… The butler is presumably still there.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Outbuttling.
Tim Sackton: I think that's everything.
Tim Sackton: Books are just books.
Tim Sackton: the organization is, you know, exists as far as Calypsois exists.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Yeah, I… I think so. I also think, like, There are…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): there's more… there's a lot more that could be built out about the organization, and feel free to build it out. Like, it's interesting to think about some of the Drancorian,
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, work on the multiverse… Like, as being with people who are connected with it.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): I think it occupies this interesting place between, on the one hand, like.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Genuinely keeping the world safe from threats.
Tim Sackton: Minimum.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): On the other hand, not… Worrying about how they do it.
Tim Sackton: out.
Tim Sackton: Sorry, last thing before you go, do you have a preferred canonical name for the prisoner?
Tim Sackton: You call them the first at the very end, but I wasn't sure if that was the actual name.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): No, the order called him the Thirst, and the Feylord called him the Child, and he's also the… I gotta ponder that. I'm not sure I have. I think the prisoner in the 27th room is the great…
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Like, that's.
Tim Sackton: This is, like, a generic, perfectly fine. Okay. Okay, I think that's it. I'm gonna update a bunch of these, and I'll…
Tim Sackton: If you find things that you want me to change in Telcoverse, let me know.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Mmm… Awesome.
Tim Sackton: Okay, good night. It was really fun.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): bud.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Thanks for making your world a… Taldarverse is unreal! Like, the… what you can build from that thing is unbelievable.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, it's gotten… it's gotten sort of out of hand, and I… yeah. Kong's gonna use AI to index it all, so he can, like, query.
Rev. David Schwartz (he/him): Cool.
Tim Sackton: Yeah, tonight.